Hello, and welcome to Working With Databases. After we've set up our PHP system and learned the basics of
working with forms, we would like to process form data even further, and that's where databases come into play.
We'll first set up a database and we will use a web-based tool, which also uses PHP by the way, called
phpMyAdmin. Then we'll do the standard database operations. We will insert data, we will read the data
back from the database, we'll update the information in the database, and finally, we will delete the data.
However, before we even try to connect to our database, it has to run first.
So, if you haven't done it already, make sure that your database is running properly on your system.
In my case, I have XAMPP installed here, as we saw previously, and as you can see here in the Apache control
panel as part of the XAMPP Control Panel, Apache is running, so the web server is already there and works,
however, what does not work is the database yet, MySQL. So what I'll do is I'll start the database and after
a short MySQL is backgrounded with green, so it's running and we can work with the database.
It might look different on your system, you might need to go to Windows Services, for instance, and then
start the MySQL service if you haven't started _____ service on other systems the database might need to be
run manually from the command line. It depends on your system, but just make sure that the database runs,
and from then on you can continue.