In order to configure the database and create a new database for our PHP code, we need to administer
MySQL. One of the most convenient ways to do so, and one that runs on virtually every platform that has a
web server in PHP, which means every platform, is to use phpMyAdmin.
PhpMyAdmin is an open source, web-based administration tool for MySQL.
You can download the source code from phpmyadmin.net, and in most cases you just have to unzip the source
code into your web folder and, well, then run the index.php file and you'll get a very beautiful, slick, and
very functional interface where you can have access to all the tables that are part of your MySQL
installation. You can create new databases, you can import and export data, you can add users, and so on and
so forth, very convenient, so that's why we use this very tool to set up a new database for our PHP code.
If you're using XAMPP, this is how phpMyAdmin looks when you run it directly from your XAMPP installation,
because XAMPP does come with phpMyAdmin installed and already configured for you, just run
localhost/phpmyadmin in your browser and you're done. If you've installed it manually, chances are that you
get a login screen where you login with your MySQL credentials. By default, the XAMPP installation is a
very insecure setup. It's using a user called root and an empty password.
Of course, that's not secure at all, however, that's the way the default setup is, and we will use this
default setup for our experiments here, so I will stick to that setup.
Of course, you can create a user of your own, and if you have a hosting partner where you'll eventually host
your website, then you will have a database there and you will have a specific user name and password
credentials for that database so you have to use that. So just adapt it to your needs, I'll use the easiest,
but of course not secure way, just for the sake of simplicity and not to waste time with too much setup.
Now let's have a look at the phpMyAdmin Home page. We'll have a couple of tables already installed as part
of the default installation. We see some general information about the server and in the top bar we can go
to the databases section where we'll see a list of databases, and we can also create a new database, and
that's what I'm about to do. So I create a new database, I'll call it php, click on Create, and then that
database php has been created, it turns up down here. If I click on the database name, I can create tables.
On one database I can several tables and a database server, as we have one here, can hold several databases.
Now let's create a table for a small example. This example will be based on the form example from the
previous module where we stored users, so how about calling that table users, which will have a number of
columns. Now for the sake of simplicity, we will not store all of that form from the previous module in the
database. Instead, we'll just store select data from it, so I would say we will have four columns which we
want to use, and these four columns are as follows. First of all we have an id column, a column that will
eventually hold an _____ value and identifier for our database entry.
This will be important later on. Now, if you scroll a little bit to the right, we see a couple of
attributes that we can set for the database field, and one of it is A_I, auto-increment, so essentially
we'll say, okay, assign automatically the next available value to that field.
There are fields that are probably more interesting. So we will have a name field of type, let's say, VARCHAR.
How long can the name be? Let's just say 20 characters, it could be more it could be less.
We have a gender field, which well, essentially could hold another data type since we only have two genders
in our form, let's just stick with the VARCHAR of length 1, and we of course have our favorite color,
which is also VARCHAR. It might be a little bit longer. So that's the basic setup.
We have a table, users, with an id, a name, a gender, and a color, and we'll save that, and the database is now
prepared for our next steps. So we could browse the database. Of course, there is no data within the
database yet, so we could add data to the database. We could run SQL statements, we could create an index,
a lot of things, and most of the MySQL features are directly mapped into a feature in phpMyAdmin, so it's a
very, very convenient tool, but we'll now leave that convenient tool and write a tool of our own, because
we'll now use our own PHP code to talk to the database.