Before we actually write some code, a couple of disclaimers. First of all, there is more than one way to
achieve what we want to achieve. We have already decided on using MySQL as the database of choice,
however, even that gives us several possibilities of how to talk to the database from PHP.
PHP offers a variety of options. We've chosen the most common one, but even that option we chose provides
different APIs, an API that uses OOP and an API that uses functions.
We've decided to use the function-based API because that seems to be more in line with what we've covered
in the previous module. Also, we do not do a lot of error detection or prevention, or even error handling
in our sample, because our focus is on how to communicate with the database, so we skipped that for the sake
of what we want to achieve here and what we want to learn, but of course, in a real-life project you need to do that
definitely. We use XAMPP installation, which as I mentioned previously, comes with an insecure default root user
that is allowed to do everything without any password. Of course, that's just the local system, but of
course on a system that's accessible from somewhere else, from the outside or from someone else within
your own home network, you need to use a different setting, but we skipped that because every system is
different and it's hard to give a very, very common guideline here, except from create a unique user that
can only access the database we just created _____. And finally, we do not spend a lot of time on designing our UI,
well, actually almost no time on designing the UI, so it's not pretty, but it will work and that's the main thing.
And with that, let's start.