In order to communicate with MySQL from PHP, we use the mysqli extension that ships with PHP, and in most
installations it's enabled by default. We have here our configuration file, php.ini, and you see here that
we have a line extension=php_mysgli.dll. On systems other than Windows, the file extension is different,
but the rest is the same usually. And since there is no semi-colon at the beginning of that line, the
extension is part of our PHP system and is automatically loaded. If you look at the PHP info output, you
will also see an entry for mysqli. You will also see that the name mysql shows up a few more times in
php.ini, so there is a mysql extension, there is also a pdo_mysql extension, but the most common one used is
mysqli, so that's what we are using in order to access our database from PHP.
The first step is to connect to the actual database. The mysqli extension provides the function
mysqli_connect for that. As I mentioned previously, there is also an object-oriented API, in which case you
would need to instantiate the mysqli class, but there is no difference in functionality, so we will use
the function-based one, and that's the one here using mysqli_connect.
You provide server name, username, a password, and if you want, and usually you want, you also provide the
name of a database. The return value of mysqli_connect is a resource.
It's kind of a handle or pointer to the database connection.
You will need to use that handle, that resource, when communicating with the MySQL database later one, because
on one page you could connect to several MySQL databases, and PHP, of course, always has to know which
database you intend to send some SQL statement to, so you have to use the return value of mysqli_connect.
At the end of the day, or well, at least at the end of the script, you may also want to close the connection
to the MySQL database, and mysqli_close is the command that does exactly that.
As you can see here, you have to provide the database handle as an argument so that PHP knows which MySQL
connection to close. There's good news. The built-in garbage collection or garbage management of PHP
takes care if a script is at its end all open connections are closed anyway, however, from a performance
point of view, it's always a good idea to close a database connection as soon as possible in order to free
up resources. When communicating with a MySQL database, mysqli_query is the function most commonly used to
send an SQL statement to the database. The first argument for mysqli_query is the database handle.
Once again, PHP has to know which database to talk to or which database connection to use.
The second argument is the SQL statement. As you can see here, we have an IO SQL statement you have to
take care about double and single quotes so that you mix and match them correctly, but basically what
happens then is that this statement is sent to the database and the database then processes it.
As previously mentioned, we do not do any error handling here, so we do not specifically check whether that
works or goes wrong, but basically if the statement is correct, if the user has sufficient privileges,
then the statement goes through. The database will process it, and in that case, since we have an INSERT
statement, we'll store the new information in the database and we will try that with our small example right now.
Since, however, our form will allow users to provide data to be stored in the database, we have to be very,
very careful from a security point of view. The danger here is called SQL injection, because if we send an
SQL statement to the server, and part of that statement is data from the user, maybe the user sent us
another SQL statement, like drop table or delete something, so we have to prevent this.
There are several ways to do this using the mysqli extension. We are using an approach that escapes
dangerous special characters. In order to escape those special database characters and any user input,
we can use a function that's part of the mysqli extension called mysqli_real_escape_string.
The mysqli_real_escape_string function expects two arguments at least.
The first one, once again, is the database handle and the second one is the value to escape.
Now in this example here, we have value1, value2, there are no special characters in there, but if the values
contain, say, single quotes, then those would be properly escaped for MySQL.
So basically what we do here is we assemble our SQL string. We are using sprintf.
Sprintf is like a printf, a formatted print, however, it doesn't directly print
something out, but it returns it as a string, so that's what the first s stands for.
So we have again an INSERT INTO table statement, however, we have two placeholders in that statement with
the percentage sign and an s; s, again, stands for string. And next up we will provide the values for
those placeholders. In the values we make sure, using mysqli_real_escape_string, that all special characters
are properly escaped. And only after we've done this we will send the SQL statement to the server using,
once again, mysqli_query. There are additional _____ you could use, so for instance, if you expect
a number value from one specific form field then you could check whether that's really a number and doesn't
contain, say, any letters, and the mysqli extension also provides a mechanism called prepared statements,
where you first create a statement and then assign the dynamic values, which will be later inserted into the
database, but for now this is actually good enough, so that's what we'll use
not only here on the slides, but now also within our PHP editor and in our code.
To save some time, and especially typing, I have taken the liberty to already prepare some basic HTML for
our insert form. I've used the form from the previous module and removed a couple of fields, I just left
three back in, the username, the gender, and the favorite color. I also left in the Submit button and
the validation logic, however I removed the other fields. The idea now is the user can fill out that form
enter some data, and once the form is submitted, we create a SQL statement out of the information from the
form and send it to the database. So what we will do is, first of all we connect to the database,
mysqli_connect. The host is localhost. The user, and I've discussed this a bit, is root and empty password,
that's the way XAMPP is rolling, but of course you will have your individual user here, and we need the name of our
database, which is called php. Then we need to create the SQL statement, and I'd like to use sprintf for that.
So I store the statement in a  u variable and have, well, some basic SQL before I escape user input.
I am not using single quotes, I am using double quotes, because I need single quotes within the SQL
statement so less escaping for me if I use double quotes here, otherwise, there's no difference.
The statement will probably look like this, INSERT INTO, and then the name of our table, which is called
users. Then we have a set of columns, VALUES, and another set of VALUES in that case.
The columns we have set up were called name for the username, gender for the gender, and color for the
favorite color. Next up are the VALUES, and I'll put them in a new line so it's a bit easier to read.
We'll have three VALUES, all of them conveniently strings, and I'll use the placeholder syntax of sprintf here.
So that's the statement INSERT INTO users (name, gender, color) and the VALUES,
and what I'll do next is I will add values for those placeholders.
Remember that in the form we've created PHP variables, name, gender, color, which already hold user input.
However, there still might be special characters in them, so we need to escape them.
We can use mysqli_real_escape_string, we use the database connection, and then the value of the first one
is $name for the username, and then I'll just do copy and paste and add the values of $gender, and finally
$color. That's the statement. Now the statement should be safe and sound.
And finally, I can do mysqli_query. I can use the database handle from before, provide the sql string I just
created, and I am done, and well in the end I could do a mysqli_close in order to free up resources.
Also I could output something like echo, User added so that we know what we've done.
Let's go through this again. First of all, we connect to our database, then we assemble our SQL statement,
making sure that all the special characters are properly escaped, and then we send it to the database.
The connection will be closed later. Basically that's it. Let's run this in the browser.
So we launch our insert script, we have our UI here, and let's just add a new user, say Rasmus, who is
male and who's favorite color is blue, Submit, User added. And now let's add debbie, who is female,
who's favorite color might be red, Submit, again it says User added.
If you go to phpMyAdmin, you see the database was empty before, the table was empty before.
I click on Browse again, and now we see that we actually have two users in our database.
So adding the users worked pretty well. Now we can add additional users, we might also consider removing
the pre-filling of the form maybe after a user has been added, so that afterwards it's easier to add a
completely new user without having to delete previous input, but basically our insert form is now done.