Reading information from the database requires an extra step. The first step is easy.
We, once again, use mysqli_query and send a statement to the database, this time a SELECT statement with
previous PHP versions, what you now had to do was you had to use a while loop and then slowly iterate
over the database results, and it looked a bit weird and was especially a bit tricky to understand if you
were very new to PHP or knew other languages where this is so much easier, however, the mysqli extension also
provides a very, very convenient feature, and that feature is that you can iterate over the return value
from mysqli_query, if there are return values, with a foreach loop, so very, very easy.
That's how a foreach loop looks in PHP, a tiny bit different from some other languages.
So in the foreach loop, the first argument is the list of items you would like to iterate over.
Then we use the keyword as. And the next argument is a variable that doesn't need to exist before.
That variable will hold the current value in each iteration of the loop.
So foreach ($result as $row) means iterate over $result, and for each iteration put the current element in $row.
In our case, $row is an array that holds all values from the current entry, the current record in the result set.
So if we had a table with two columns, "co11" and "col2", then we could use that array syntax here in order
to access the values in those columns in the current record. So pretty easy, send SELECT statements
to the database, and then iterate over the result in order to get all data so you can process the data and,
for instance, output all the data you got from the database.
Let's start with a very simple UI to list all users currently in our database.
I will just add a new PHP File, which I will call select, because we are sending a SELECT statement to the
database. I'll start with some basic HTML, because we need an html file essentially.
And as title we'll use PHP once again, and in the body section all the magic will eventually happen.
I think the good way to output just the list of users is to use an unordered list, and in that unordered list
we have list items like this, maybe rasmus who is (male), and in order to show the favorite color as well,
we could invent this in a &lt;span&gt; element, and that &lt;span&gt; element will get a style.
The style is color, whatever, blue for instance. So that's what I'd like to output, but of course I need
some PHP for that. So let's start with a php block right in here.
We could do some generic stuff like connecting to the database at the very top of the page, for instance,
or even in an external file, but for now we just put it right in here so we'll see everything on first look.
Once again, we connect to the database with mysqli_connect. The database is running at 'localhost' using
the 'root' user and a not-so-secure password, and we'll use the database php.
And our statement is pretty simple. It's SELECT * FROM users. Well, this will be sent to the database
using mysqli_query, and we get our result back. And now we can iterate over that result.
So, foreach ($result as $row). It doesn't matter how I call _____ variable, but that's the name that I will
be using within the foreach loop. And well now I have to output a list element for each row in that result set.
So I could use printf, and within printf I just paste the string, however, I do not say color: blue, I say
color and then a placeholder. Same goes for the name, which gets a placeholder, and the gender.
And after I've done that, of course I need values for those three placeholders.
They are in $row of, first up is the 'color', and then we have $row of, next up is the 'name'.
And finally we have $row of the 'gender'. However, remember that's data in the database, so all database
special characters have to be properly escaped, but maybe not html special characters, so we need to escape
those before outputting it. Do not forget this. So we have htmlspecialchars, which we will put around each
of those three values, fix the indentation, close the parentheses, and now we are done.
We connect to the database, we send the SELECT statement to the database, we iterate over the result, output
it, well and at the end, of course, we can close the database connection.
Let's try this out in the browser. _____the insert form, we'll now go to select.php, and indeed, we get a
list with two items, two entries, because we happen to have two names in the database.
We see rasmus in blue, debbie in red, and if we have a look at the page source, we also see that the color,
the name, the gender, they've all been put into that string, into that list element, and we have two list
elements which were printed using our PHP code. So reading out the data has been pretty easy so far.
Let's continue with other SQL statements.