In order to update the information in the database, you can send an UPDATE SQL statement.
That's actually all you need to do, essentially, so we use, once again, sprintf here in order to gather an
UPDATE SQL statement. Once again, this statement will contain dynamic data, at least in our example where
we'll have data from a form. Since this data might contain dangerous special characters, we have to escape
them, once again, using mysqli_real_escape_string, escaping them assembling the SQL statement using
mysqli_query in order to send the statement to the database. Well, and then the data is updated in the
database. So, with all those things said, let's go directly to our example and we'll _____ update form.
I've already created an update.php file. It looks exactly like the insert.php file before we added code,
because basically we need the same form, however, this time we do not want to insert something, we would like
to update an existing record. Conveniently, the form already has some pre-filling logic, so we can use that
logic in order to create an update form. We have to first retrieve the record which we would like to update,
so how do we do that? First of all, we need to know which record to update.
Each entry in our database has a number, an id, in the id column. The idea now is that we call the update.php
script using update.php?id= 5. So we provide the id of the record to update as a URL parameter, as
a query string component. The first step will now be to read out that component.
So we check, is this set, so do we have $_GET of 'id'. It's part of the query string, so $_GET will hold it.
So if this is set and if this is a number, we will use it. How can we find out whether the value $_GET of 'id'
is a number? There are several ways of doing so. We could try to convert the value, which by default is
a string since it's part of a query string. We could convert it to a number and then see what the
result is. If the result is 0, then either the id was 0, which usually is not a good value, but
anyway, or it wasn't a number and conversion just said, well, I can't convert it, here is a 0.
That's one way. The other way would be we use one of the built-in functions PHP provides for that.
One of them is called ctype_digit. Ctype_digit has a _____ value, in our case $_GET of 'id', and checks
whether it consists of digits only. Of course, there could be some input like 010101 that's only digits,
but well it's probably not a good number, but 010101 is 10,101. So, well, it kind of is a number still.
We'll just use that for now. So if we have a value in 'id' in the URL, and if it consists of only digits,
well then we are good to go. So we store it in the variable right now because we will need it later on.
We'll leave it as a string so we don't do any explicit conversion into an integer, because later we will
stuff it into an SQL command and SQL string as well, so that's where we stand.
However, what do we do if we do not get an id? Hmm, well, then we should somehow error out.
I told you before we won't do much error handling, but at least in that case we should do something.
And what I would like to do is I'd like to show you a specific feature.
I'd like to redirect to another page. If I try to call the update page without any valid id or no id at all
in the URL, I'd like to redirect to the list of users, to our select.php page.
We do this redirections using an HTTP header called location, and the php function that sets such a header is
called header, and we say 'location' and then select.php. This command issues the http header, thus the browser
requests the select.php file from the server, essentially aborting the script here.
There's one catch though. Depending on your configuration of PHP, this will give an error because we have
already sent html to the browser, so we cannot just redirect, so we have to move this code up to the very
beginning of the page in order to avoid any issues. So I'll just do cut and paste, and there we go,
just indent a little bit to make it a little bit prettier. Okay, so we check the id, and then essentially
we have an id value. If not, we redirect to the select page and now we can take care of the actual code.
In our page here, we have the validation logic starting here, and the validation logic always runs when we
have submitted the form. Now if we do not submit the form, what we could do is we could read out the
current record. You see that name, gender, color, they are defaulting to empty strings, but we would like
to actually load values from the database. Well, you have already seen how this is done more or less, so
let's add some code for this right here. Once again, we connect to the database, so we do a mysqli_connect
to 'localhost' using 'root', empty string, and accessing the php database.
We store the return value in a variable because we need it when we set a query.
What does the query look like? Well, we do a SELECT statement, SELECT * FROM users, however, this time we
have a WHERE clause WHERE the id= and then a specific id. Which id do we use?
Well, we already stored it in a variable, so let's just put it here at the end of the line, id.
So we now have SELECT * FROM users WHERE id=, let's say 5 if you call the page with update.php? id=5.
this will be sent to the database using mysqli_query, and now all we need to do is we have to read in the
result. There are specific functions in PHP which we could use now in order to retrieve one specific
result, however, in order to reuse what we have previously seen, and so that we do not need to add some
extra functionality in here, we cheat a little bit, and what we'll do is we will use a foreach loop.
Since we only got one record back, this foreach loop just runs once, but we can just reuse the code we had
in our select.php file a bit earlier on. So for each $result as $row, there is only one row, but in that
case that's fine, we just pre-fill $name with $row of 'name'. We pre-fill $gender with $row of 'gender'.
And finally, we'll pre-fill $color with $row of 'color'. Now the values from the database are in the
variables. The form fields will be pre-filled with those values, so the only thing remaining is, once the
form is submitted and once the form data is okay, we will essentially need to write that to the database.
Let's do this right away.