I once again connect to the database, so mysqli_connect to 'localhost' using
our user and also connecting to the php database specifically. Then I copy together the sql string, so
sprintf of something, which is to be defined. Now this time I need an update statement, so UPDATE users
SET, and then name= value, so I set the name to something using a placeholder, I set the gender to something
using a placeholder again, and finally the color to, you guessed it, a placeholder again.
Very, very important now, this statement will update each and every record which we obviously do not want,
so we need to add a WHERE clause, easy to forget that until you try it.
So WHERE id= another placeholder. Next we fill those placeholders, remember we work with data coming from
the user, so there might be special characters inside. We need to escape them in order to prevent SQL
injection, so we do mysqli_real_escape_string of, in that case, name, and then, once again,
mysqli_real_escape_string of the gender, and finally mysqli_real_escape_string of the color.
The fourth placeholder is the id, but remember we read the id from the URL so it's user data, however, we
checked whether the id only consists of digits, so we know only digits, so we do not need to do additional
escaping, so we just put in the id here, we have valid SQL string, which we send to the database using
mysqli_query. Afterwards we output what we've done, so User updated.
We could also redirect to the overview page, which would be fine as well, but I think this is good enough for now.
And finally, we close the connection to the database, which actually we could also do down here, so we
close the connection here as well, just some cleaning up, alright.
Now next up we need to run the update.php file in our browser, however, if we do so and do not provide an
id in the URL, we get redirected to the overview page, hmm, that's what we want, but actually we would like
to see the update.php page in action, so we need to provide an id, and we need to add the id when we actually
run the page. However, there is one page that already knows all of the id's, because the page knows all of
the users, and that's select.php. Here we already output all users, so how about we add an extra link here.
Looking like this, a href="update.php". Link text is edit, however, the link doesn't go directly to
update.php, but to update.php?id= placeholder. How do we fill that placeholder?
Exactly, htmlspecialchars of $row of 'id'. We just read out the id from the database as well, and stuff it
into that link. So by updating the overview page, we provide a very convenient link to the update _____.
Here we have the overview page from before again, showing just the names at the moment.
I reloaded because we changed the select.php page, and now we have to two edit links going to update.php
id= 1 and 2. Let's edit debbie. You see the form is already pre-filled with debbie, female, and red as
her favorite color. Let's just change her color to, let's say, green.
I submit it, and the user has been updated. We can prove that by going back to select.php, and now as you
can see, debbie has been updated because now her favorite color is green.
So it was a bit of work, there's still some cleaning up which we may want to do, but still, we now since
we have learned how to pre-fill a form, how we can also pre-fill an update form and then create the update
statement required to update an individual record in our database.