The sole missing important database operation is deleting. So we need an sql DELETE statement.
And that's it, we put together the statement, once again, taking extra care of escaping special characters
so that no one can enter something we do not want. We use mysqli_real_escape_string, and finally send the
SQL statement with the sanitized data to the database. Deleting is always tricky because you have also to
make sure that only the right people can actually access the PHP script that deletes information.
In our example, of course, it's simple. We are the only user, we are the administrator, and it runs on our
local system, so we are good so far, but of course, in the real world you might want to give some additional
protection to that script, for instance, password protection or something else.
But, basically, the actual process of deleting information is just sending a DELETE statement to database.
So let's finish up our little project.
An implementation of deletion is usually quite a bit of work because you have to make sure that the user
really wants to delete a record, so you have to add a kind of, are you sure, yes, no screen.
Also, you will need to make sure that the user can only delete those records that the user is allowed to
delete. You have to make sure that no one from the outside can actually trigger the deletion.
We do a very, very simple implementation. The simple implementation just rounds up what we've done so far
when working with databases, however, in the real world you need to add some extra safeguards just as a
disclaimer at the very beginning. But now let's start with the page, I add a new PHP File, I call it
delete.php because we will have to use the delete SQL statement. I will add some basic html in here, so I
just add our PHP title, and then I have a body section, and well, basically that's it.
We won't have that much of a layout, however, what we will want to do is we want to call this page using
delete.php?id=5, and then record that the id 5 shall be deleted. So as before with the UPDATE script, we
need to find out whether actually we get an id as part of the URL, and we do that at the very beginning.
So we just do an if (isset($_GET('id')), so if the value is set, and if it consists of only digits,
so if it's ctype_digit($_GET('id')), and then we can, well, later delete the information.
For now we just store it in a variable, so $id = $_GET of 'id'. Otherwise, we redirect to the old view page
as we did before. So 'Location: select.php'. Alright, now the variable is set, and in here, because I'd
like to output that the record has been deleted. If we delete it, we can then use this id variable because
if we come so far, it definitely has been set. Now let's once again connect to the database, so
mysqli_connect to the 'localhost', using our 'root' user, and accessing the php database.
How does the SQL statement look like this time? Well, I just do a DELETE FROM users WHERE id=, and now I
can, and this really is an exception, now I can really put the id variable in here.
I have double quotes, and if I use a variable name within double quotes, the variable name is replaced by
the value of the variable. I have checked before that $id only consists of digits, so there's no SQL
injection in here. This is one of the very, very few cases where I don't have to escape using
mysqli_real_escape_string. And now I'll send this to the server using mysqli_query, and echo out how happy
I am that it all worked hopefully, User deleted, and finally I can close the connection again.
So it's a rather short script, and whenever I'm calling now, let's say delete.php?id=1, I will
delete the record with the id 1. Again, this is not a very secure way of doing that, there is no, are you
sure, yes, no. If someone triggers me, for instance, by sending a link, but there are other possibilities
to run this script, then I just delete an entry. But in order, as I mentioned, to round up the example,
this is a very brief way of doing deletion, but usually when you delete you have to add some additional
checks, of course. Now, again, same as with the update script, it's probably a good way to directly link
to that delete.php script with the correct id, so let's go to the overview page again and add, after the
edit link, a delete link as well. I'll just put this in a new line, and this time I call it delete,
and it goes to delete.php, however, the argument which I am providing is still the same, so $row of 'id'.
So, once again, we changed the overview page, linking to delete.php using the correct id query string value,
and in delete.php we do delete the record.
Here is the old overview page. Let's reload it. After reloading, we now have a delete link here.
Sorry debbie, it's nothing personal, but I'll go here, User deleted.
So if I go back to the overview page, reload it, debbie is gone, only one record left in my database, so the
script worked as expected.