We achieved quite a bit in this module, because we were now successfully talking with the database using all
the standard database operations with PHP. In order to do so, we first set up our database.
We were using phpMyAdmin in order to administer on MySQL Server, one of the most convenient ways of adding
databases, users, tables, looking at data, and so on, and so forth.
PhpMyAdmin can also be very nicely installed at your hosting provider, but of course, you have to make sure
that you're the only one that runs phpMyAdmin in order to administer your databases.
So, maybe after configuration of your database, remove phpMyAdmin from your server or use password
protection or some other safeguards. After we have set up our database and we've set up our table, we
wrote a UI in order for reading data, writing data, updating data, deleting data, using the mysqli_
extension PHP provides, and the mysqli functions in order to communicate with the database server.
SQL injection is one of the greatest dangers for database-based applications because a user might be able
to send malicious content, which in turn is sent to the database and the database interprets it as an SQL
command, which we do not want, so we were escaping special characters and thus avoided SQL injection.
And, once again, we did not cover the object-oriented interface for the mysqli extension.
We also did not cover other extensions which allow us to talk to a MySQL database, but the features set is
more or less the same, so you are good to go now and can use PHP to talk to any MySQL database, and you can
read data, write data, and do all the operations you want. Although our sample application works as
expected, we are still not done. There are so many more features we might want to add.
One of them, and that's probably the most pressing one, is authorization/authentication,
so it's time to move on.