Hi, and welcome to Pluralsight. My name is Christian Wenz, and I would like to help you get started with
PHP, the world's most loved and most used web-scripting language.
During the course of this module, I will give you some background information on PHP, tell you why it is so
popular, and then install PHP on a web server so that it can serve PHP content.
Once everything has been set up and is working properly, we'll do an obligatory Hello World! application,
however, it's a more sophisticated version of Hello World! than you may have seen before.
But what better way to start talking about PHP than with a quote by the man himself, Rasmus Lardorf, the
inventor, creator, and first developer of PHP. He once said, "I've never thought of PHP as more than a
simple tool to solve problems", and that's exactly the approach and the vision of PHP, to solve problems in a
very pragmatic, but still good to high quality fashion. Lerdorf, back then when he created PHP, had a
problem to solve himself. He wanted to _____ dynamic content of his web server, but didn't want to use Perl
or the other technologies dominant at that time for that purposes, so he created his own language, which
would eventually become PHP. He first chatted with his peers, and then he chatted with the world, and the
next step was world domination. PHP is very popular. It's used by both smaller websites, smaller blogs,
more simple applications, up to very, very large and very complex websites such as Facebook, for instance,
who use PHP a lot. So, PHP is very pragmatic, quite easy to get into, so you do not need a formal background in
computer science to create excellent PHP applications. For this course, you will just need some basic HTML
knowledge and a knowledge of any programming language doesn't hurt, but it's not utterly required.
Now let's have a look about what PHP generally is and let's have a look at more information on that.
PHP stands for PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor, and the approach PHP is using can be seen in that definition.
PHP is usually embedded into hypertext, meaning into HTML, and PHP is actually a preprocessor, so PHP
then has a look at that HTML with some PHP code in it, and then works on that PHP code and executes it.
PHP's home page is php.net, not .com, php.net, and that website contains a lot of information about the language.
The Home page features the latest versions of PHP, so at the time of recording this, the most recent version
is 5.5.15. It will certainly be a higher version number once you are watching this.
We also have access to the documentation, which is very exhaustive, get information about upcoming
conferences, and much more information.
Depending on which statistics you're using, you can say PHP has a market share of more or less 40% of the web,
40%, so 2 out of 5 websites run with PHP. That's an enormous number, and that's higher than any other
competing technologies. One way of looking at the dominance of PHP is by referring to the TIOBE index.
The creators of this index use a variety of sources and technologies and measurements and metrics in order
to create a monthly list of the most widely used programming languages, general programming languages, not
just web programming languages. So currently we have the TIOBE index of August 2014, and PHP is on position
number 8, which is pretty good. One year ago it was even number 5.
Now since the beginnings of that index, since 1999, PHP has always been in the top 10, which is an amazing
achievement, especially considering how many very well-known programming languages are in that index
as well, and also how many well-known programming languages are behind PHP in that index.
Probably one of the main reasons why PHP is so popular is that it supports most operating systems and most
web servers. So PHP runs under Linux, under Windows, under Mac OSX, under Solaris, under other even more
exotic operating systems, and it supports the Apache web server, the IIS web server from Microsoft, and many more.
So we have a web scripting language that is rather easy to learn, it's proven in the real world, it has a
huge market share, and a legion of developers that can help out each other, it is in the top 10 since over
15 years, and runs almost anywhere, so it's a pretty safe bet to use PHP.