In order to install PHP, we first have to acquire to download it.
For that we have two options, either we can go to the PHP Home page and the PHP website has a download
section where we can get both the source code and pre-compiled binaries of PHP, or if we are Windows users
we can go to Windows.php.net where we find Windows binaries of PHP.
The PHP Download section focuses on the PHP source codes or if you want to build PHP by yourself, that's the
way to go. Otherwise, there are links to downloads for specific operating systems, most prominently Windows
on the windows.php.net. That's a specific website just for Windows users where the PHP Windows team, which
in part is even funded by Microsoft, provides up-to-date releases of PHP compiled for Windows systems, not
only for the IIS web server for Microsoft, but also for Apache web server and other systems,
but it separates it from the rest. Other operating systems like Linux, for instance, have package managers
which can install PHP with the web server. Some operating systems even come with PHP already installed or
at least built-in. So depending on your operating systems, the steps to get a working PHP system up and
running might a bit different.
One of the most convenient ways to get started with a PHP setup is to use an all-in-one installer, which
both installs the web server and PHP, and maybe some other useful software as well.
There are several options, and the one we have chosen is a product from apachefriends.org.
Those friends of Apache provide very popular distribution calls XAMPP.
The A stands for Apache, the M for MySQL, which is a database which we will cover later in this course, and
the first P stands for PHP and the second P stands for Perl. The X signifies that XAMPP is not tied to a
specific operating system. There are versions for Windows, there are versions for Linux, there are versions
for other operating systems. And the basic idea behind XAMPP is that you have one installer and that installer
installs you all required software packages and they come preconfigured.
So not only does XAMPP install you an Apache web server, and not only does XAMPP install you PHP, _____ the
web server is also configured so that it can use PHP right away. So that's really, really convenient, and
probably the easiest way to get your first own system up and running for development purposes.
The Download section of apachefriends.org provides XAMPP for a variety of operating systems.
You see your Windows, Linux, and some others further down. And what you basically do is you download the
package and then you get a kind of installer, which you just have to run and then everything is set up
automatically for you. I happen to have the XAMPP installer for Windows here, so I'll just run this and
show you how it works. Again, if you have a different operating system or a different _____ of web server,
don't worry, there are detailed installation instructions for you on the PHP Home page.
The XAMPP installer first warns me about User Account Control and that I should not install XAMPP into the
Program Files folder because it's harder to write PHP files into that folder later on, and I'll adhere to that.
But the most important step is which components I want. I can pick and choose what is installed by XAMPP
and what I do not need. Now you can pick anything, because later you will choose which of those components
are actually running, but if you are certain that you do not need some of those components you can just
deselect them, and that's what I will be doing right now because I do not need Apache, that's mandatory.
I do need MySQL choice the database for later. I do not need an FTP Server or a Mail Server or an application
server, so I deselect those three. I do need PHP, I even cannot deselect it, but I do not want Perl.
I will need phpMyAdmin to administer the database later on. I do not need Webalizer.
I will probably need Fake Sendmail to test sending emails out later on.
The recommended installation folder is usually a good choice, so I'll just stick to that.
I do not want more information about the Bitnami Company who provides installers that also configure
applications like WordPress or Joomla! with the web server and PHP I don't need that right now so I deselect
that, and well, then I'm ready, and the distribution is installed on my system.
This will take a while, so I will use advanced video editing techniques to fast-forward to the end of that
installation, but what basically happens is that all files required for our PHP, all files required for the
Apache web server, and so on and so forth, are copied into my system, and then configured so that the system
is ready to wrap, and we're done. The installer now provides us with the option to start the XAMPP Control
Panel, and that's a very important tool for XAMPP because it's a kind of management console that gives us
easy access to the components we installed. We can start those components, we can stop them, we can even
install them as a service. So we are focusing now on Apache, we can start Apache, we could also then if
Apache is running, stop Apache. We can also install Apache as a service if we click on the checkbox on the
left so it's automatically running once the machine boots up. At the moment, I just want to start Apache,
so I click on the Start button, and after a short while Apache is running and we can have a look at the
running system. In order to do so, we just fire up a web browser and go to localhost, and then have a direct
access to the XAMPP installation. We have to pick a language just once, it just remembers it, and then we
get the XAMPP Start page which looks like this. So we see the XAMPP version, we see the version of PHP
being used, and we have access to several options and further applications.
So, for instance, we can have a look at the status of the installation which tells us which services and
components are installed and running. We get access to the documentation, to components, etc., etc.
We can also have access to various PHP sample applications which just prove us that the system is up and
running correctly.
And again, using XAMPP or one of the other all-in-one tools is not mandatory.
You can install PHP manually as well, and the best way to start doing that is to go to the PHP online manual
at php.net/install.
There you'll find detailed information on a variety of systems, so you see Unix systems, Mac OS X, Windows
systems, different versions, different type of web service, so a lot of information so that almost all cases
are covered by very exhaustive information here in the PHP online manual.
So installing PHP is actually pretty easy. Just download PHP or a preexisting installer, and then you are
ready to go, ready to get started with your own custom PHP code.