In order to produce a working PHP application, we both need a working setup, and of course, working code.
Let's start with the setup. Now we already have a web server, and the web server runs with PHP.
Then we will eventually write PHP code and usually that PHP code is put within HTML files.
so we have regular HTML pages, and wherever we think that PHP is needed, for instance, to create a database
or to output the current date, we just put in the PHP code. As applications get larger and we separate them
into individual modules that are reusable, those modules very often are purely PHP.
So we can also have files which only contain PHP code. So both approaches exist and it's a matter of the
size of the application, personal preference, etc., so there is no wrong way of doing things and there is not
just one way of doing the right thing. Once this setup has been created and we know that we either have an
HTML page, where we need to put PHP into or we have PHP files, we have to take care about the file
extension. The file extension used by PHP by default is .php, and that's also the way XAMPP and the other
installers and the PHP website's installation instructions are set up.
So by default, files which have the .php extension are processed by the web server so that the PHP code is
actually running. We could change that, but that's the way everybody is using that, even Facebook.
For writing the PHP code, we need an editor or an IDE. Since PHP files are text files, any text editor will
do, as any text editor will do for HTML pages. However, of course, a more advanced editor that maybe
supports PHP and gives us syntax highlighting for PHP is beneficial in order to make less mistakes.
Now the editor of choice, of course, is a matter of personal preference.
You will have your preferences and I have mine. The editor I'm using for creating PHP content and PHP
applications is a product called PhpStorm by a company called JetBrains.
This is a commercial editor, so there is a free version that only runs for a certain amount of time, and I
was very happily paying for that editor, but do not think that you need that editor in order to follow along
for this course. It's just a personal preference. You can use your editor of choosing, preferably the
editor you are using for your HTML content, as long as the editor boasts some PHP support,
this really helps things, but again, you can pick whatever editor you want, as long as you can create text
files with PHP in it. Now, in those files may be an HTML file or may be a purely PHP file.
We need the .php file extension and then we can put code in.
Let's do this right away. I'm here in the htdocs folder of the xampp installation, that's the base folder
for the web server. And I create here a new folder for us called php-get-started, so when going to
localhost/php-get-started, we get to the files we are about to create in our editor.
Here's my editor, PhpStorm, the php-get-started folder we just created already open, and I can add here a new
file, for instance, an HTML File. However, that specific editor, when adding the HTML File uses the .html
file extension and we need the .php file extension, so I'm using a PHP File.
I name it helloworld.php and you already see here in the template that's used, a specific syntax token,&lt;?php.
This is a sign for PHP running on the server that PHP code is following, so PHP on the server knows,
okay, this is not HTML here, this is PHP code, and we can mix those.
So what we can do is we can create a simple HTML page here and then add PHP to the mix.
I'll do this right away. So I'll start with the HTML DOCTYPE, I add an &lt;html&gt; element, in the &lt;html&gt;
element I have a &lt;head&gt; section with a &lt;title&gt; for the page, and I have a &lt;body&gt; section.
And in the body section usually I would do something like this. I have a paragraph, and in the paragraph I
would say Hello World! However, since I want to use PHP, I can add PHP code in here, so I use &lt;?php, and
everything following is PHP code, until the PHP code ends with ? and closing angle bracket, which was added
here automatically by the IDE. So everything between here and here is PHP code.
Now let's write some simple PHP code, and probably the easiest way of outputting something with PHP is by
the echo command and as an argument for the echo command we then use a simple string, which is then output
into the HTML and later sent to the browser. So we use a simple string, for instance, "Hello World!", so same
as before. We have to end this with a semi-colon, and that's it, we have a simple HTML page, and the HTML
page contains a PHP section, and in the PHP section we have echo "Hello World!" as our first and very, very
simple PHP code. Let's run this in the browser. So we go to localhost/php-get-started, that's the name of
our folder, and then helloworld that's the name of our file, and we see Hello World!, which might not look
that impressive, however, if we have a look at the page source, we see indeed Hello World.
We do not see that there has been any PHP code, because the PHP code was run on the server.
The browser just receives the end result, Hello World!, there's no &lt;?php, there is no echo, just the result.
So we saw that PHP code is delimited by &lt;?php and ?&gt;, the code is output exactly where we put it in the HTML
page, and we saw echo. However, this was a traditional Hello World? with simple text.
We can do better. I create a new file, and this time I call the file phpinfo.php.
Of course, the name is arbitrary, but I have something specific in mind, and this file just consists of
&lt;?php block, and in it I call phpinof(); and I'm done. In the browser, I go to that page, and you've seen
the page is really simple, just one command, phpinfo, I mean what could the output possibly be of that simple
command. Well actually, quite a lot. We get a very long page consisting of a lot of information about
the installation. We see the PHP Version number, we see information about the system we are using, the grading
system, the build date, even, of PHP, and if I scroll through it we see configuration, for instance, the
Apache configuration, so the configuration of the web server, and we also see which extensions to PHP are
installed, so which additional features are installed. For instance, there is something called bz2, which
has to do with file compression. We see further down curl, which is a very popular tool to do HTTP requests
We see a date extension, which lets us handle date and time information.
We see exif, which is used by digital cameras, and the image is produced by digital cameras, so that's
metadata, and so on and so forth. A lot of stuff coming up, mysql, mysqli, some of this has to do with data base access, and so on and
so forth, a very, very long page, and finally credits. So a lot of information just by using this one
command, phpinfo.
I like to call this the luxury version of "Hello World!", because it essentially is Hello World.
Traditionally, Hello World! is being used in order to just check whether the system works and whether we
can run programs. so we could do a Hello World! like we did before, however, the phpinfo "Hello World!"
not only proves that the system is running, it also tells us how the system is running, how it is configured.
On our own system, it's just a way to have a look whether we configured it correctly, whether all
extensions we're using are properly loaded, etc., on our hosted system.
It's even more convenient because we see how the host configured the system, we see whether the host
has installed and configured all of the extensions they promised they would do.
We also see if there are any additional features installed which we might be able to use.
So it's very, very convenient having looked at the phpinfo output.
Of course we shouldn't put it on a public facing page and even link it, because other people might also be
interested in the information, it's just for us so when you have a new hosting partner, create a phpinfo
file, put it on the web server, run it, save and print the output, and then you can remove the file again,
but we just see that way which PHP version we have, which also is an important piece of information, and
also the configuration and what's installed, so super useful, and Hello World! version that's so much
better than just outputting some text.