As I mentioned before, PHP has an excellent documentation. You'll find it on the php.net website in the
manual documentation section, however, there are some very, very useful shortcuts, so PHP supports a lot of
vanity URLs. So if you append, say, a function name, or the name of a constant or some other special terms
to the URL, so if, for instance, you go to php.net/phpinfo, you go to the manual page for phpinfo,
this works in most cases. So let's have a look.
As you can see here, php.net/manual gets you to the PHP Manual and you're automatically redirected into the
language version of your browser's language setting. Of course the English version of the PHP Manual is
usually the one that's most up-to-date, but as you can see here there are several other languages supported
as well. Also we have the shortcut URLs so we can go to php.net/phpinfo, and we are then redirected to the
phpinfo Manual page, and as I mentioned it works for most of the built-in functions.
Also there's some generic terms like install, so if we go to php.net/install and this leads us to the Installation
section including some other not-so-common shortcuts like install.windows, which leads us to, you may have
guessed it, the Windows Installation page. Obviously that only works when you're online.
Your IDE might provide you with an offline version of the manual, however, there is one on the php.net
website as well. In order to get access to that offline version of the PHP manual, go to the Downloads
section of the php.net website and then on the right you have the documentation download link.
This leads you to a page where you can download the manual in a variety of formats including one single
big HTML file, many HTML files, and probably most convenient, an HTML Help file.
So you have the usual chm format, as long as you have a chm viewer, which is automatically the case on
Windows, in order to have a look at that content. There are two versions of the HTML Help file.
One that just contains the manual and another one which also contains user notes, and user notes is another
very useful feature of the PHP online manual. If you go to an arbitrary manual page like the phpinfo,
mail page we saw before you'll see that there is some description about that function, however, at the end they are
User Contributed Notes, which start right here. And what happens here is that it's a created list of user
suggestions and user postings providing additional information, workarounds, common issues, etc., etc.
Of course, not all of the code snippets in there and not all of the advice in there is always valuable
or even factually correct, but most of it is pretty good, it gives you some very common workarounds,
some very common have to knows about certain pages in the PHP Manual and features that come along with it.