Before we reach the end of our brief introduction, I have to tell you a little bit more about the history
of PHP and the pivotol version numbers PHP saw in its past.
It all started in 1994 when, aforementioned, Rasmus Lerdorf started working on a set of tools, which at first
he only used for himself, then showed them to some of this closer peers in University.
One year later, in 1995, he released those tools and called them Personal Home Page Tools or PHP Tools.
Usually this would be the end of the story, because well, those tools were used at the university, and they
were also used by some people outside the university, but still, the traction wasn't that high.
It was pretty successful, but not that many people actually used it.
It wasn't mainstream yet. However, some time later Lerdorf was approached by two Israeli students, Zeev
Suraski and Andi Gutmans, and they approached him and suggested some changes for the way PHP was parsing code.
Lerdorf was very happy with the suggestions by those two students, and told them to go ahead.
They did, and the result was PHP version 3, which also was the first PHP version to support Windows, which
was not used that much for hosting back in the day, but of course, still had that gigantic market share for
developer systems and especially for desktop systems, which many people used even for programming.
With version 3 of PHP, its market share and usage skyrocketed. It was used all over the world, even more so
when 2 years later, in 2000, PHP 4 was a new major release. It had a new core, the so-called "Zend Engine".
Now Zend is the name of a company Suraski and Gutman set up. You can see that the name of the company is
built from the two first names of those gentlemen. Zend employs a lot of developers of PHP, but it doesn't
really control PHP. It is still an open source, community-driven effort.
Zend just sells a couple of additional services and software for PHP, for instance, Zend Studio, an IDE for PHP.
Now PHP 4, with this new core, the Zend Engine, featured more OOP features because PHP 3 actually had, well,
no features for object-oriented programming, PHP 4 had a little bit more of that.
It also came with series session support. And again, more and more people were using it, more and
more websites were built based on PHP. The next major release was PHP 5, and it took the project 4 years
in order to make this release. PHP 5 comes with a lot of new features, but many of those features are
around object-oriented programming. There are many new OOP features, well new for PHP, other languages had
that since years, but still, a lot of OOP was added, so more and more professional applications, more and
more professional code could be developed with PHP, thanks to that version.
The number after 5 is 6, and so the PHP developer team worked on PHP 6, which among other things, should
come with full Unicode support. However, this proved to be quite a task, and so eventually that project was
abandoned. PHP was supposed to come with a lot of new features, Unicode just being one of those features.
So eventually it was decided that all of the other features were good enough for a new major release, just
the Unicode stuff would not make it, so they released PHP 5.3. PHP 6 never saw the day of light.
PHP 5.3 came with many, many new features and was the new de facto standard.
So although it's only a minor version number update, there was 5.1 and 5.2 in between as well, by the way,
5.3 is the new PHP version, the new big version after PHP 5. After 5.3, followed 5.4 and 5.5, and as I'm
recording this, PHP version 5.6 is about to be released. Just a few days now and whenever you are
listening to this, 5.6 will have been released, so it will be the most current version.
Maybe there is even a more recent version of that. 2014, at the time when I am recording this, also saw
two other new developments. One is that the final update for 5.3 has been released so there won't be any
new updates for PHP 5.3 as of August 2014. That means if you should still be using 5.3 or your hosting
provider is still using 5.3, you will have an outdated version, so you should seriously consider upgrading
your PHP version. Also, the version number for the next major version of PHP has been determined.
There was a long debate whether it should be PHP 6 or PHP 7 or something entirely different, but since PHP 6
is still remembered by some as that version that never came to be, the team decided to call the next major
version PHP 7, so let's see when this will come out, but until then 5. something, at least 5.6 is the version
we are about to work with.
So in conclusion, we saw that PHP is very, very popular. It's supported by most operating systems, most
web servers, and a very large number of developers. You saw how to install PHP on a specific system.
We learned about phpinfo, the Hello World! on steroids. We learned how to use the owner manual, for
instance, to look up how to install PHP on another system or another web server, and we had a quick dash
through the history of PHP and relevant version numbers. So we had a great start, and I hope you are looking
forward to continue to getting started with PHP.