In this final module of PHP Get Started, we'll wrap up our small sample application, introducing a few more
PHP features along the way.
First of all, we will talk about including files, so we have either code or HTML markup in external files,
which basically is not a bad idea, then we need to load or include them in our PHP script, and we'll have a
look at how this is done. We will also talk about a very important topic, we'll talk about storing
passwords. Obviously you shouldn't store passwords in clear text, but even some of the encryption or
hashing mechanisms are not recommended these days, so we will have a look at a secure implementation which
comes with PHP. Finally, we will cover state management from a PHP perspective, so we would like to remember
information, to remember data, and HTTP doesn't allow us to do that actually, but there are workarounds and
PHP implements a workaround, and that's very easy to use and we will use that in our sample application.
But first, let's start with Include Files, so external files. I mean, in general it's a good idea to split
up your code and also your markup in individual files so you can reuse markup, you can reuse implementations,
and it's also a bit easier to work on a project with several people at the same time,
and PHP has a built-in mechanism to handle those files to be included.
If we have external PHP files, so if we have PHP functionality that resides in an external file, we can load
that external file from our PHP script so we can use the functionality.
If you use, say, object-oriented programming, and PHP offers a lot in that area, then that's more or less
a must so that you can split up your classes into individual files, but even if you do not do this it can
be beneficial to put functions that you use from several PHP pages into one file so that you only have one
copy of that functionality and only have to maintain this one file with the functionality.
Now PHP offers four commands in order to load those files, include, include_once, require, and require_once.
I think the names of those instructions are pretty self-explanatory.
So include just loads includes an external PHP file at the very position where you include it, so it will
be included and it runs. If you include the same file several times, well, it will be loaded and executed
several times. If you use include_once, however, only the very first time you load one specific file it
will be loaded and executed. All the subsequent calls to include once with the same file, well, they are
kind of ignored. If the file you want to include doesn't exist, you get a warning, however, the PHP script
continues running. If you use require, instead of include, then the file you want to include needs to exist.
If you do require filename.php and filename.php does not exist, you'll get an error, and the PHP script stops.
Well, and finally, require_once is require, but it checks before whether the same file has already been
included using require. If so, it's not loaded and executed again.
So, just have a look at those two files. We have our PHP file, you see, &lt;?php, it requires the hello.php
file. You don't need parentheses after a require or include or require_once or include_once call.
Well, and then echo ' World', and we have the hello.php file at the bottom, which also starts with &lt;?php
because it contains php code, no markup, and that file echoes 'Hello'.
If this is run, what basically happens is that we first load hello.php with the require call, so the php
script does echo 'Hello', and only then the echo ' World' is executed because it's put afterwards in the
original PHP file. In the end we get Hello World, and that's basically what include and require and
include_once and require_once do for php files. Now if you would like to put HTML markup into an external
file, we cannot use this mechanism really well because include and require is called from PHP where PHP code
is expected. However, there are several other functions in PHP for loading, let's say, regular files,
and the most convenient one here is to use readfile. Readfile loads a file and outputs it immediately.
So if you, say, have a navigation in an external file and you would like to use that navigation from several
individual pages on your PHP website, you could use read file and read file then loads the navigation.
You only have to have the navigation once, you only have to maintain it once, and can then include it into
several of your pages.