Let's try out include files, and specifically including files with HTML or CSS so we have to use a readfile.
One idea, for instance, would be that we have a common navigation for all pages within our small sample
application. So let's do exactly that. I will add a new file and well I could call it HTMl File, I could
also give it a specific file extension so that I know exactly that it's something I include, but
it depends on a variety of factors. I'll just call it navigation.tmpl, for template, .html.
And in that file I will create a very, very simple navigation to be used in our application, so I'll just
do an unordered list, and each list element is a link to one of those pages we've worked on before, so I'll
just call them according to the SQL statements they represent. So we have INSERT, we have SELECT,
we also had UPDATE, and finally, we had DELETE. So I create this and then I will add some CSS.
I could add the CSS to a global CSS file for the application, but just for the sake of simplicity and so
that we have everything in one file, I'll just add it directly to the template.
And what I'm doing here is basically telling the browser how to display the list, because I want that don't
have those bullet point things, and I also would like to have the list items next to each other, not
underneath each other. So I will just do a rule that says, list-style-type equals to none, so I don't want
to have bullets. And also what I'd like to have is that the individual list items that they are next to
each other, and I can do this by telling them to display, not as a block element, as they would usually be,
but as an inline element. So that's my template, navigation.tmpl.html, and wherever I would like to have
that template I can call readfile. So let's maybe start with the insert.php page.
A good position for the navigation would be at the very top, so right here.
So I could do readfile, and then 'navigation.tmpl.html', and this will load the navigation right away.
I'll copy that to the clipboard, and I'll add it to the other files as well so that we have the same
navigation in all of our four pages of our application. I just have to put this within php right here,
because it's php code. And finally, delete.php, that's a page with very little code, and now let's add some
extra code. I will call to readfile. And that basically adds the functionality to our application.
Let's validate our efforts in the browser. So we'll go to localhost/php-get-started and then say
select.php, and indeed, we have our navigation here at the top and we have it on every page, so including
the external file worked very well for us.