I am back here within phpMyAdmin, because I would like to do some changes to the database we've been using
for our sample application. I choose the php database, and within the php database under Structure, I
have the users table, and within the Structure of the users table I see that we currently have four columns.
I'd like to add 2 more, so I say 2 more columns at the end of the table is fine.
I click Go, and now I have to provide the names and data types for those additional columns.
One will be called password, and let's say it's a field of VARCHAR, 255 characters, where I will later store
the password, or something similar to a password. Also, I'd like to store whether any user has
administrative privileges, so how about adding a field, isAdmin, and as a data type we could use a Boolean
or let's just use a bit of length 1, and by default, the default value for that is 0.
So by default a user is not an Admin. I click on Save, and then the schema of the database has been changed,
so if you go back to the structure you can see that now our table consists of 6 columns.
Now that our sample application database table supports passwords, because we have a new column for that,
we should actually store passwords in the database, or shouldn't we?
Well, no actually we should not, because it's always a bad idea to store passwords in a database without
encryption. Someone might succeed in stealing our database, and then the passwords are just gone.
So if you have subscribed to a service on the web and you use the forgot the password feature because you just
can't remember your super secure, very long, very many special characters password, and you get your
original password back via email, that's usually a sign that the service stores your password without
encryption, or they use an encryption they can reverse, both of which is not acceptable.
So since _____ _____ at least if passwords were stored in a web application these passwords were hashed.
So, there are algorithms that determine a kind of fingerprint for a password.
So two different passwords have different fingerprints, and there is no way to retrieve the password from
the fingerprint, however, only the fingerprint is stored, so if someone steals the database, only the
fingerprint is stolen, but not the actual password. Formerly we were using MD5 or SHA1 algorithms for
doing that hashing, however, nowadays with modern hardware, and in the case of MD5, even with not-so-modern
hardware, they can be broken, so you should not rely on that. Now PHP provided a one-way encryption that is
secure for several versions now, but it was not very easy to use. However, with PHP 5.5, a new programming
interface, a new API was created, is now part of PHP, which makes it super easy to encrypt/hash passwords
so that the encryption cannot be reversed, however, we can later validate whether any given password matches
the encrypted information in the database. It's called the Password Hashing API, and you do need PHP 5.5 or
higher. There are _____ implementations for earlier versions of PHP, but I'm assuming that you'd use a
recent version of PHP so you can use the Password Hashing API, which is enabled by default in PHP so you
don't have to do anything. This is how it works. You use the password_hash function, provide a top secret
password, and fashion the algorithm, which should be used to encrypt or hash the password.
The best option is the PHP constant PASSWORD_DEFAULT, which uses the best available algorithm at the time.
The idea behind that is that a future PHP version might come with a newer or better algorithm, so you
always use the latest and greatest. Still, old hashes still work when later verifying a password against
that hash, but it's a good idea to use PASSWORD_DEFAULT if you would like to use a specific algorithm _____
constant for all supported algorithms available as well, but PASSWORD_DEFAULT is a good value.
Now the return value or a possible return value, I have to say, of that password hashing can be seen here.
So, well, it has not very much to do with the top secret password anymore, but that's something you can
securely store in a database. It's not very useful to an attacker at the moment, it's just a hash, but what
happens if later a user logs in and provides us with a password, let's say, topsecret, and you'd like to
verify if that password matches the information in the database. Now there's a kind of a _____ function
of password_hash, it's called password_verify. Password_verify expects first an input strings-- a password,
and then a hash. And we are reusing the $p variable from before and return value of password_verify is a
Boolean value, either true if the password matches information of the hash, or false if not.
So when logging in, just read out the hash from the database, run password_verify, and then you know whether
the supplied password is the one that has previously been stored as a hash in the database or not.