Let's use the Password Hashing API in our sample application. We have an insert form, and so far we can
have a user with gender and color. Let's add a password for the user so that we can register user with a
password or even users can register themselves. Let's go down to the markup.
We have the username here, and let's just add a password field real quick.
So we have a password field, which looks similar to a text field, but has a different type, and of course
a different name. And for pre-filling out that field, well actually we shouldn't pre-fill password fields,
we could add a new $password variable right here and then pre-fill it, but you shouldn't pre-fill password
fields, you have to enter this each and every time, so let's just remove this here.
Now, what we then need to do is we have to stick with our validation, so let's just copy the approach and
start with a password variable which defaults to an empty string, and I copy and paste this validation code
for the text field, because the password field is basically the same.
Instead of name I just write password -- $_POST will be  the variable name, so $_POST of 'password'
two times, and otherwise, $password is the variable for $_POST of 'password', alright.
Now after the validation is out of the way, we have to amend our database code.
Instead of adding three values to the database, we now add four, name, and password, and gender, and color,
and of course we need one more placeholder here. We fill that placeholder with mysqli_real_escape_string,
and then, well, not password. Why not password? Because in that case we would store the password in clear
text in the database. Not so good, so let's use the Password Hashing API.
We call password_hash of the password using the default encryption algorithm, and we store this in a variable
called, let's say, hash. And what we store in the database is now the hash value, not the clear text
password, we store the hash, we generate with the Password Hashing API.
So whenever a new user is registered with a password, that password is hashed or encrypted, one way, and
then sent to the database, so no clear text passwords in the database.
We will try that in the browser right away. We go to the INSERT page, which now features a Password field.
We register user, christian, Password, well, topsecret, I won't tell you what it is, and the Gender, any
color will do, Submit, User has been added. Let's go to phpMyAdmin, go to Browse, we now have two users
and the user christian has a password, and that's not topsecret, what I entered, but it's the hashed password.
And I will now do something manually in phpMyAdmin, because we'll not create a UI for that.
I go to Edit and I will change the isAdmin field to a 1, because I want to be an admin.
I would later like to use the administrative features of our application.
So I'll store that, and if we have a look at the contents of our database again, and scroll a little bit to
the right, we'll see that, yes, user christian is an Admin, rasmus is not.
So you see how easy and convenient it is to use PHP's Password Hashing API to store, not passwords, but their
hashes for later verification use.