The user's password is safely stored in the database. Let's see how we get the password out of the database now.
I create a new file. I'll start with an HTML File, and I call it login.php.
Now the editor still wants to add .html, so I rename the file so that we have a real php file, and in that
php file I'd like to add a very simple login form, just to see how we can verify the password in the database.
It's actually not that hard. We use a form which uses http "post".
Action is empty string, which means we send the form data to the actual current php script, and then we have
two fields. So we have the User name, which is a text field, and let's say it's called "name".
And we have a Password, and that's the password field, input type="password", name="password" as well,
easy to remember, and we have a submit button, input type="submit", and as a caption we use, let's just say
"Login". And then we write some PHP code to verify whether that login would work or not.
First of all we determine whether the form has been submitted, so if isset $_POST of 'name', so do we get
a user name, and do we also get a password. We could also check whether we get a string as we did before.
We could also check if there is something inside those fields or if they are just empty strings, but I
would say so far this is a good start, and now we connect to the database as before.
So, mysqli_connect('localhost') using a user, a password, and connecting to a specific database provided by
its name, we then put together an sql statement. We use sprintf once again, and let's just SELECT * FROM
users WHERE name=, and then use single quotes again, so maybe double quotes for the string are a bit nicer
so we don't have to escape the single quote, WHERE name= placeholder.
The password is out of the picture at the moment. It will be added to the picture later, but first of all we
have to find a value for the placeholder, and of course, once again we use mysqli_real_escape_string with
the database connection and the value to escape the username  $_POST of 'name'.
That's the statement, and then we have mysqli_query, $db, and then the sql statement, and get a result back.
Now, of course, we hope that these results contain one data set, one record to be exact, so how do we do that?
So, of course, we could try the foreach loop again and either the loop runs 0 times or it runs at least once,
but I think in that case we should specifically fetch the first record.
And there is a function for that which returns a row, and that function is called mysqli_fetch.
And you see there are a lot of fetch methods, and we use assoc, because it gives us an associative array,
that's what assoc stands for. So we just call mysqli_fetch_assoc of the result, and then $row is an
associative array with all the data we got back, if we got data back.
If not, $row is in that case false or null, which in PHP, at least in our context, is pretty similar.
So what we can do is this. We just do if ($row), because if it's false enough, then essentially it's just
like false, and the statement from the if will not be executed.
However, if there is something in $row, we can process it. If not, so let's start with else right here,
we just do a 'Login failed.' And well, if you have something in the row we are interested in two things,
we are interested in the password and well actually it's not the password, it's the hash, and that's what
we have in $row of 'password' because that's the name of the column.
We might also be interested in isAdmin, which is $row of 'isAdmin'.
We won't use this right away, but we might use it later. So we got the hash from the database for the given
user, and we have to verify whether that hash matches the password the user just entered.
So what we do is this, if (password_verify), and then first the password, which is $_POST of 'password', and
next after the password we use the hash, $hash. And if that matches, so if we can verify the password
against the hash in the database, then we can do a 'Login successful.'
Otherwise, again we have 'Login failed.' So this 'Login failed.' essentially means password wasn't correct.
This 'Login failed.' down here means well the user doesn't exist, but we shouldn't give the user too much
information as to why logging in did not work, so let's just stick with 'Login successful.', 'Login failed.'
Well, and in the end we just do mysqli_close of our database connection.
So we connect to the database, we check whether we got the user, we check the password hash from the user,
verified against the password the user supplied upon login, and then we either get a yes or no.
After removing the semi-colon here, let's run this in the browser.
I am loading login.php, and I try to login with a user that doesn't exist and an arbitrary password, and
login failed. Then I try to log in with christian, my user name, and some arbitrary password, Login failed.
And finally, I try to login with my user name and topsecret, logging in, and Login successful.
So, our login form works, well at least it tells us whether it would work if there was some additional
logic, but we'll come to that in a bit.