If you read through the HTTP specification, you will see that HTTP is a so-called stateless protocol.
So basically HTTP doesn't remember a thing, however, in web applications we have to remember a lot of
information, for instance, what has the user done so far and which user is it anyway,
state information, language settings, and so on, and so forth. So an important topic for web-based
programming is state management. We need a mechanism to store information across requests, and there are
several ways of doing that, and what php offers among other things, is to use a so-called session which
uses in turn, cookies. The server sends a cookie with a unique identifier, usually a long string consisting
of digits and lowercase letters, to the browser, and the browser then stores this cookie information and
on all subsequent requests, that cookie value is sent back to the server.
So basically we get a session id, say, abc12345, and with each and every request to the server we send this id,
abc12345, back. So the server might not know who we are, but the server always knows, ah, that's user
abc12345, so let's store some data on our server-side database or in the file system about abc12345.
And if we eventually login, then the server knows, okay, that's user xyz, and the session id of user xyz is
abc12345. There are many implementation details about PHP doing specifically on the server, and what
happens on the client, but so far, for us, from a programming perspective, there are only a few things we
need to know. First of all is, how can we activate that session support?
Sessions are activated by default, and available in PHP without any further configuration.
However, this session cookie is not automatically being sent from the server to the client.
We have to instruct PHP to do so, and we do that by calling a function called session_start, which among
other things sends the cookie. There are other technical options as well, but by default it's a cookie.
Of course, a cookie is an HTTP header, so we have to call session_start before any HTML output is sent to
the client, just to be on the safe side. So session_start starts the session support, sends the cookie,
checks if a cookie has been sent as part of the HTTP request, and so on, and so forth.
So it sets everything up for us. We do not have to do a thing.
The only thing we have to do is to access the superglobal $_SESSION array, which is an array like $_GET,
$_POST. It's available everywhere, however, the nice thing is we can just write to it and read to it.
This actually triggers quite a bit of work in the background, so for instance, PHP has to find out which
session we have, and has to store the data at the right place. If you read out $_SESSION, PHP has to retrieve
the information on the server from the right spot. Essentially what we are only doing is we work with an
array. We store data in the array, and then on the next page, if we again use session_start, the array is
still there, so we can memorize information, for instance, which user is currently logged in, and so on,
and so forth. So a very convenient mechanism which requires minimal work for us, and a bit of work from PHP,
but well, that's what we have PHP for, right?