Let's finish our sample application, especially the login page. First of all, I'd like to have the navigation
on the login page as well, so readfile, and then our 'navigation.tmpl.html' page.
But, of all the features I like to add, I'd really like to finish the login mechanism.
So far we only get the information, hey, you're user name and password combination would have been correct,
but you can't use it, or it would have been wrong, but you can't use, and now I'd like to use state
management, especially sessions, in order to store whether we are logged in, and of course, which user is
logged in. I would like to do that, and since I might need session management and session_start especially,
I'll do this at the very top of the page. Remember, session_start outputs a cookie, and thus needs to be
called before any HTML is sent from the server to the client. Let's do this right away.
So this starts the session management, which sets everything up for us, and now we can work with the
$_SESSION array. I will use the code from down here and just move it up to the top of the page in our
php block here. And if we logged in successfully, I do not want to output it, I just write it in a string
error, a message = 'Login successful.', and here message = 'Login failed.', and here also message = 'Login
failed.', and the default value is $message = is an empty string, and I output just the $message string
down there, so I go and how about this, I put out $message. Remember, double quotes means variable names
--the string will be replaced by the values of the variable, so I just output the $message variable in
a paragraph right here. Alright, but what happens if the login is successful, that's the most important
thing? Well, then I would like to store some information in the session, for instance, that I am logged in
or even who is logged in. Maybe it's useful to know who is logged in so we know that the user name is in
$_POST of name, and also in $row of 'name', so we could just do $_SESSION of 'user' =, and then let's just
say $row of 'name'. So I store the currently logged user in the session.
Now the session is stored on the server, so it's harder to manipulate than just, say, information that's
stored in a cookie. So I just stored it on the server and just sent the user the session id, which doesn't
contain any real information. So I can do that. I can also do $_SESSION of isAdmin =, and then $row of
isAdmin, or since we've already stored this in the variable, $isAdmin.
So I store both the name of the user and whether the user is an administrator or not.
So that concludes our login page. Next we have to use that information in those pages which should, say,
only be accessible for an administrator, especially the UPDATE and the DELETE page should only be available
for an administrator, maybe even the SELECT page should only be available for those with special privileges.
Let's add a new PHP File, because it's the same code for UPDATE and DELETE, and maybe even SELECT, because
we just would like to check is the user logged in and is the user an admin, and I call this auth.php for
authentication. And what we do here is, we just call session_start and then we check whether the user is an
admin. So how do we do that? We check if $_SESSION, because that's now available since we've run
session_start, is available, and in $_SESSION we could check whether we have a user name.
What we could also check is if isAdmin is set. Now for our implementation so far, we do not need to know the
name of the user, we just need to know whether it's an admin or not.
So I just check $_SESSION of 'isAdmin', so if this is set, and if $_SESSION of 'isAdmin', remember it's a
bit field from the database and contains a 1 or well, true, in our case, so we can just use $_SESSION of
'isAdmin'. So if the user is logged in and isAdmin is true, then all is good.
Well, actually in that case we don't have to do anything, however, we would need to do something if the user
is either not logged in or not an admin. So if not is set, ! means in that case not of course, if the isAdmin
variable is not set, which means you don't have the variable at all so the user is not logged in, or if
not $_SESSION of 'isAdmin', so if it's not true, in that case we don't have an admin or we don't have a user at all.
In that case, the user had to go to the Login page, so we redirect the user with header, and then 'login.php'
as the new location, so we redirect the user right to the Login page.
And this auth file will now be needed on all of those pages that should only be accessible for administrators.
So one of them is the update.php page, so what we do here at the very top is require on then the file name,
so we have auth.php, and we use require because if the page isn't loaded and our validation code that
checks for admins is not loaded, we cannot continue obviously. So require 'auth.php', here an update php,
and well, let's add it to delete.php as well. And in the same fashion you could add this code or similar
code to the select page. For instance, on the select page you might consider only checking whether the
user is logged in, but not if it's an admin _, well, that depends on the application at hand.
A quick look in the browser will tell us whether everything works as expected.
So let's go to, say, the update page, which redirects us to the select page because we didn't provide a URL
parameter. Now, let's go here to, say, edit the christian user, and as you can see, we were redirected to
the login.php page because we are not logged in. So let's login now, christian, and then our topsecret
password, Login successful. I go back to the overview page, I go to the edit page, and now I am here in
the editing UI, because now I am logged in, the application recognizes me, grants me access to the page, and
does not require me to actually login again, because I am already logged in.