We have added quite a number of little and not so little things to our sample application in this module.
So we saw how PHP can include files, external PHP files with code, and also files like HTML or even CSS files
with markup or other information, and we saw how to use those files from within our PHP code.
We saw in require, require_once, include, include_once, and readfile.
Also, we had a look at the Password Hashing API, which is a super easy way to actually store passwords in
a secure fashion, so much better than MD5 or SHA1 or some of the other hashing algorithms or even storing
passwords in clear text, which is certainly a very bad idea. Then we had a look at sessions and saw how
easy it is to use sessions from PHP code, you just have to start session support and then have the $_SESSION
array where we can write stuff to and read stuff from, and this array is retrieved and is retained between
individual HTTP request, so we keep the data within that array. And finally, and most importantly, I hope you
enjoyed getting started with PHP, and I wish you a lot of fun with this language and all of the tools and
libraries around that, and happy PHP'ing.