Hi, and welcome to Working With Forms. Forms are the only way in HTML that offers users to actually
communicate with the website, input data, and so on. The only other means we have for that is following a
link, but of course that's not very interesting from an information-gathering perspective.
So we will have a look at forms. We will first cover the basics, so how does a form look like in HTML,
a very brief look at the most important form elements, but before that a look at HTTP.
What happens if we do submit a form, what happens if we an HTTP request?
Then we will move on to PHP and we will have a look at how we process form data, so how we can get the form
data from the HTTP request and also later how we validate a form, so how we can make sure that all mandatory
fields are filled out and that all fields contain valid data, and if that does not work, how we prefill
form elements with previous validators, so quite a lot to cover.
Let's dive right in. In HTML we have the &lt;form tag, and the form tag has a couple of attributes.
The two most important ones are first the action, so the target of the form submit.
If we set it to a blank string, it's the current page, that's the pattern we will use in this module, by the way.
And the second important attribute of the form tag in HTML is the method attribute.
The method attribute holds the HTTP verb, or the HTTP method. The HTTP specification defines quite a lot
of those verbs, of those methods, PUT, DELETE, HAD, OPTION, TRACE, and so on, but the two most important
ones are GET and POST. Now the default HTTP verb is GET. You will have taht when you follow a regular link
for instance. If you submit any data with that request or if you submit a form using HTTP GET, the form
data is appended to the URL. So if a question mark and the name equals value, and name equals value, and so on
and so forth. Obviously there is a size limit to those URLs. There is a size limit in the web browser,
there is a size limit in the web server, there may also be a size limit in the proxy that's between browser
and server, so you may not want to make the URL there very long. So for most forms, except for simple
search forms, usually we do not use GET. However, if we use GET, we have a PHP array, $_GET, which holds
all values and lets regular variables _____ arrays also available within PHP functions without any need
to use the global keyword to import it in the function _____. The second most important HTTP verb or HTTP
method is POST. In POST we do not have that size limit. We could even send files, we can have file uploads
when we use POST. POST doesn't put data at the end of the URL, but instead if we have HTTP headers and then
a blank line, we have the actual body of the HTTP request and that one will hold the POST data.
There are several ways how to encode the data in the request, but the default it's name = value, and
name = value, etc., just like with GET, however, in the HTTP body, and not in the URL.
The appropriate PHP array that holds all of the data is $_POST.
Let's have a look at how these requests look like. First there is a GET request, so we have the URL.
And as you can see at the end of the URL there are several name value paths.
We can only see the first few of them because the line is so long so it got cut, but that's the most
important part of the GET request. After that you will see a couple of additional headers, for instance,
headers that show which browser we are using, which language setting we have in our browser, where we come
from, let's refer a header, etc., etc. For our POST request, as you can see we do not have any information appended
to the URL. We have more or less the same set of headers, however, at the end of the headers we have a blank
line and afterwards we have our Name value fields, so that's basically how HTTP GET and HTTP POST may look like.