We continue with the next type of fields, the radio buttons and checkboxes.
Now for those we first have to find out whether they have been activated when the form was submitted.
It's a bit easier for the checkbox, it's a bit more complicated for the radio buttons because we have several
radio buttons. We need to find out which one has been activated, if any.
Then if we have found it out we have to make sure that using HTML means those are activated again.
The HTML attribute we need to use here is called checked. We go back to the code.
Let's start with the checkbox at the very end, and if the checkbox has been selected, we need to add checked
but when do we add checked? Well, if we add it if the value of $tc, remember the variable that holds the
current value of the checkbox = "ok". So, once again, it's time for a php block in here, and in that php
block all we are doing is if $tc === 'ok', then we just echo out checked.
And I also echo out a blank space character so that it nicely fits into the HTML markup.
And this very approach is the same we will be doing for the radio buttons up here, same thing.
We add a php block, and in that php block, after I re-fix the indentation, we have a look at this time the
gender variable, remember that will be set with the input in the gender field.
And if the gender variable has a value of, in that case, f for female, we echo out checked, as simple as that.
Otherwise, we don't do anything and the radio button is not pre-checked.
Same thing here, so I add a new php block and in that php block I do essentially the same thing as before,
so I do an if $gender ===, and in that case 'm' for male, and if so, I echo ' checked'.
And now this field is also properly prefilled, if it has been prefilled before, so far, so good.