Two more form fields to go, the two lists, the dropdown list and the multi-select list.
Well, it's kind of similar to the checkbox, and especially the radio buttons, but with some differences though.
If a list element is selected, we need to use the HTML attribute selected, so we had checked with the radio
button _____ checkboxes, and now it's selected for the list. The only thing remaining is to find out whether
any given element has been selected. It's rather easy for the dropdown list, because it's almost the same
as for the radio buttons. It's a little bit more complicated for the multi-select list because we have to
learn one more new array function of PHP. Let's start with the colors list, because we can only pick one
color. Basically, if for instance, this red color had been previously selected we would need to add
selected here. How can we find out whether the red color had been previously selected?
Well, we need to add a php block and have a look at the $color variable.
So I add a php block, and within the php block what I'm doing is I check if $color has a value of, and in
that case, not red, because red is the caption, we're interested in the value, so we have to compare the
values, and if the values match then we can echo out ' selected', and we are good.
Forgive me for using copy and paste, but it makes things a little bit faster, so I do the same thing here, I
just need to swap out the color code, this time for green, and finally I do the same thing for blue using the blue
color code, and I'm done here. I do not have to specifically preselect the first element, of course.
So I just check which color had been chosen, if any, and depending on the color I preselect an item.
There's a little bit more work to do for the languages, because well, I could essentially start with code
like this, but I cannot compare the $languages variable to a string, because $languages is an array.
So I don't have to check whether the languages is en for English, I have to check whether the array
$languages contains en. There is an array function for that in PHP, of course, it's called in_array, and you
see here in the editor, needle, haystack. So needle is what we're looking for, haystack is where we are
looking for it. So we are looking for 'en' in which haystack, in languages.
So if 'en' is somewhere in the $languages array, so if the user has selected a couple of languages and
English is one of them, we preselect that option. And the same thing will be done for the other languages
here, we just have to swap out the language code, so 'fr' for French and for Italian we use 'it', and well
basically, that's the check, the mandatory check we need to do in order to make this work properly.
Finally, we make the output a little bit better because we are still accessing $_POST here, but now we have
variables for that anyway, so this will turn into $name. We still need to do the HTML escaping.
We are only escaping when we output data, not when processing or validating it.
And same thing goes here, this turns into $color. This will turn into $languages, which in that case will
already be an array, this will be $comments, and finally, this will be $tc.
Now we're pretty good. We started with 30 lines of markup and code, now we have 139.
That's quite a bit, but the result should be worth it. Let's fill out the form again.
Once again, User name, top secret password, once again, forget to provide our gender, but we do provide a
color, a couple of languages, some comments, this is a nice form, accept the terms and conditions.
I click on Submit, and you see, the page is reloaded, but the data is still there.
If we have a look at the source code, we see that selected has been added here and here and here, and a
checkbox is checked, and the user name is prefilled too, so our code worked as expected.
Now let's provide a gender, but let's say forget the terms and conditions, it doesn't work,
and now I have filled out the form without any errors. I click on Submit and I get the output as expected.
So the form now is much nicer. Still some room for improvement, we don't have any design to speak of,
we shouldn't show the form if it has been filled out completely, but we have come very, very far with some
amounts of PHP code.