We've covered quite a lot in this module. First we saw that PHP puts all data from forms in the $_GET
and $_POST arrays, depending of course on the HTTP method used by the form.
So we had a POST form in our example, so all the data was put into $_POST.
Had there been any data in the URL in the query string, then $_GET would have been filled as well, although we
had a POST form. If we have a GET form, of course everything lands in $_GET.
It looked like a lot of work to validate the form, but once you validated the text field you can validate
all text fields in the same fashion. The same goes for the more complex constructs like multi-selection
lists, for instance. We also saw how we could prefill form fields, so let's say if we had a form with 10
form fields and the user fills out 9 of them correctly, at least those 9 values are kept and they are not lost
just because the user made one tiny error. Finally, we also saw how we can defend against Cross-Site
Scripting by properly escaping output, and in our case we were outputting HTML so we had to get rid of HTML
special characters in the user input. The best way to do that was to escape those special characters
with a built-in PHP function, htmlspecialchars took care of that, so we now have a fully functional and
pretty secure HTML form with some PHP in the background.