After we have covered all those basics, now let's have a look at all those form elements HTML is providing
for us, and how we can use them from PHP. First you see several types of text fields.
There is a single-line text field, there is a password field, which essentially is a single-line text field,
but the input is masked, and there is a multi-line text field. We have the input HTML element for most of
form elements. One of the very few exceptions is the multi-line text field, which is done via the text area tag.
So basically we have several fields, several HTML form types, and each of them should have the name attribute
set because we will use the name there later to access the value in those fields.
Next up we have radio buttons and checkboxes. So a checkbox is just input type= "checkbox" with, of course,
again a name and a value. And as we'll see later, if the checkbox is activated, the value is sent to the
server. If not, then nothing is sent to the server. But more interesting are radio buttons, because radio
buttons always occur in groups. There is a group of radio buttons, and you can only select one of those
radio buttons at a time. In order to do that, you have to tell the browser which of the radio buttons on the
page are in the same group. You do this by using the name attribute.
All radio buttons that have the same name attribute are part of the same group.
So how do you distinguish the individual radio buttons? Well there still is the value attribute, and the
value attribute needs to be different. So if you have a group of radio buttons, the value of the radio
button that has been selected is sent to the server, or the other radio buttons are kind of ignored from a
server point of view. And finally, we will later have a look at selection lists.
So we have the select HTML form element, and each individual entry in that list is put into HTML using the
option tag or the option element. You have a caption for each element that's within the option tag, but you
also have a value. Quite often, actually, the value is the same as the caption, however, the value is what
is being sent back to the server, the caption isn't. The only exception, if there is no value at all, then
the caption is sent to the server. There are other form elements in HTML.
Actually we will see one of them a bit later on, a button because we have to submit the form somehow, but
basically these are the ones you'll see and use most often in the web.