I have already prepared an HTML form for us to play with. This form contains those HTML elements I mentioned,
and also one or two special items, which we'll talk about a bit later.
So here is the markup of that form. It's a PHP file, because we later want to add the PHP code, of course,
but at the moment it only contains HTML markup. It contains a form and use http POST as a method.
You could also use GET, of course, but we'll use POST this time. The action is set to an empty string so
that if the form is submitted back to the server the same script is run as the one that produces the form,
so it's form.php, that's exactly what we want. We then have a single-line text input field, a single-line
password field. We have to radio buttons in the same group for the gender of a person.
Then we have a selection list with three items to choose from. By default, that's a dropdown list.
We also have a multiple-selection list where users can select more than one entry.
We also have a multi-line text input, the text area here, we have a checkbox to accept the terms and
conditions, and finally, we have a new HTML form element we didn't cover before,
we have input type="submit", which essentially is a submit button.
So once we click on that button, the form data, the input of the user, is sent to the server where we will
eventually process those data.
And this is how the form looks in a web browser. So we see the text field, we see the password field, the
radio buttons, the drop-down list, the multiple-selection list, we see the Comments field, and we see the
checkbox. Finally we have a Submit button to send the data back to the server.
Then on the server we, of course, would like to process the data, for instance, validate it or just output
it, kind of a form Hello World!, and that's what we are about to do right now.