In order to output form field input from PHP, we have to look at each and every form field and see how we
can access the data in there. We'll start with the text fields, single-line text, password, and multi-line
text. Basically, that's true for all form fields. In PHP we have two superglobal arrays.
they're called superglobal because they're also available in functions without us needing to do something
extra, which is different from regular global variables in PHP, so these are superglobal variables.
$_ GET holds all get data, so data appended to the URL. $_POST contains all HTTP POST data, all HTTP POST
information. Since our form is using the POST HTTP method, we will use $_POST.
Now this is an array, and the names of the form fields are the array keys, so we have to make sure that, of
course, every form field that we would like to process on the server does have its name attribute set, and
we also have to remember the value in that name attribute, because then if we use the element's name as the
array key, we get the actual information within the form field as the array value.
So say we have input type="text" name="txt", then $_POST of text or $_GET of text will give us the value
that was entered into the form field before the form has been submitted to the server, either using POST or
GET. From then we decide which of the two arrays we are choosing.
This general rule holds true for all text fields. So even for password fields, you cannot see the password
which the user inputs, however, it sends to the server in clear text so you can access it using $_GET or
$_POST. It's also true for buttons, so we have a Submit button. The Submit button also happens to have a
name and a value, because the value is the caption of the Submit button, so we can access, well, the value of
the Submit button clicked. This doesn't sound very interesting, however, there are two advantages of that
approach. First of all, if we happen to have several Submit buttons for one form, we can find out which of
those has been clicked. And even if there's only one Submit button in the form, if the value of that Submit
button is sent back to the server, we know that the form has been submitted, so that's an easy way to find
out, and that's what we'll do right now. Remember, our form has a Submit button with its name attribute set
to Submit, so we can use that information in order to find out whether the form has been submitted
when we process form.php or not. In order to do that, I just add a php section in here, and I check if
$_POST, because we're using POST, of submit has been set. In some other languages we would just try to
compare this to null, but in PHP we use a specific function for that called isset.
So if (isset($_POST), so if this is set, in that case we can be sure, well, the form has been
submitted, so process form, and here we can, let's say, output all the data that has been sent alongside the form.
We can individually output stuff using echo, but I'd like to use a different function here for output, one that is
very well-known in the C world actually, it's called printf. Printf takes a string, and that string contains
placeholders. There are several options for placeholders, but I'm using this placeholder, %s, s stands for
string. So we have a variety of placeholders, and after that we just add parameters to the printf function
call and this is the value for placeholder 1, and this is the value for placeholder 2.
I do this in order to be able to easily output all the data from the form.
Let's start with the actual text I'd like to output. So I'd like to output what the user entered, so I'd
like to output User name, and well, then the actual value. Afterwards I would like to output, and I'll do
this in a new line so we can read it a little bit better, the password.
You shouldn't output the password in clear text, but here, for the sake of the example, we'll do that,
placeholder, and then we just have to overwrite auto-completion here.
I'd like to output the gender, so I have gender in the placeholder for gender.
I'd like to output the favorite color and have a placeholder for that.
Also I'd like to output the language or languages, and as you guess, I have a placeholder for that.
Then further down in the form we have two interesting fields. We have the Comments text area and we have
the checkbox, so let's start with the Comments and the placeholder, and finally, we output whether the terms
and conditions have been accepted, so I do T&amp;amp;C. I have to encode the ampersand character in HTML,
because it's HTML output, and then again, one final placeholder.
Now how many placeholders do we have? I count 7, so we need 7 string parameters afterwards, so we have
number 1, number 2, number 3, number 4, number 5, number 6, and number 7.
So far so good, and now we can start filling those placeholders with actual values.
We started with text fields, that was our intention, so we have three text fields here.
We have the user name and the user name is the first placeholder, so we just do a $_POST of 'name', because
the field is called name. The password, second placeholder, is $_POST of password, because that's how I
called the field. Then we have Gender, Color, Languages, which we'll call later, and then we have the Comments
field. Comments placeholder is filled with $_POST of 'comments', because that's how the field has been called.
So, at the moment we process we output three out of those seven fields, that's a good start.
There's still some stuff to do, including some security concerns, so please make sure to watch the module
until it's very end, but this is a good start, so let's have a look how this looks in the browser.
Let's fill out those three form fields we covered. So we have a user name, let's say christian.
We have a password, let's say topsecret, whoops, I let you into my topsecret password.
And I have some Comments like, This is a nice form. I click on Submit, I ignore all the other fields so far,
it goes back to the server, and indeed, the User name, the Password, and finally the Comments are output.
It's not pretty, but it works pretty well, so let's go back to the code and process the other form field types.
But before we do so, we will have a look at those types and what we need to do with them.