Let's next have a look at checkboxes and radio buttons, because they are actually pretty similar.
We started the checkbox, so a checkbox has a name hopefully, and a value hopefully.
We actually need both of those attributes because if a checkbox is activated by the user and then the form is
sent to the server, the value is sent to the server along with the name of the checkbox.
If no value is provided, browsers usually just send on just as you can see here to the server, but of course
it's always better to be explicit about the data we want to be sent to the server, so always provide a value.
So that's what we do with the checkbox. If the checkbox is not activated, nothing is sent to the server,
at least not for the checkbox. Other form fields, of course, are still being sent to the server.
For radio buttons, remember that all radio buttons within a group have the same name, but different values.
The value of the radio button that is selected is sent to the server, once again, in $_GET and $_POST.
And it's really important that you have the individual group name.
That may not sound very intuitive because all the other form fields have their own names, but again, this
piece of information is very important for the browser to be able to tell which radio button belongs to
which group. You could have several groups of radio buttons on one page.
With that information, let's go back to the code and implement this.
The radio buttons have the group name Gender, and the terms and conditions checkbox has the name TC, so
so that's exactly what we are using. So Gender is the third placeholder, and now I'll printf string.
So let's see here we output $_POST of 'gender'. And terms and conditions are the last placeholder we have, so
we add $_POST of 'tc'. We double-check the names because otherwise that's an error not so easy to spot,
gender and tc, so this all looks good. Let's go in the browser, because that's where the truth is, and
see if that works as expected. Here we go again. User name, topsecret password, Gender, Comments, and
finally I accept the terms and conditions, Submit, and we get the Gender, and we get the terms and conditions
value. So these fields work pretty well. Only two more to go, the lists.
We have two types of lists in our example. We have a dropdown list that we can only select one element and
we have a multiple selection list where we can select and arbitrary number of elements.
Actually, lists are pretty easy, at least in the dropdown list case, because we, once again, access $_GET,
$_POST, and then we get the value of the selected element. If no element is selected, nothing is sent to the
server for that form field. If the selected element doesn't have a value, the caption is sent to the server,
but again, always explicitly set a value, better safe than sorry.
It's a bit more complicated for multiple lists or multi-selection lists.
Once again, we access $_POST and $_GET, however, since several elements may have been selected by the user,
$_GET or $_POST of name of the list, contains an array this time, not just a single value, an array of
values, of 1 value or a 5 values or however many elements have been selected.
There is a catch though. This has historic reasons, but well, that's just the way it is and you may have
noticed this already in the HTML form we are using, and also here on the slide.
If you have a multi-select list, the main attribute needs to end with square brackets.
So you cannot just provide a name of list, you have to use list and then opening and closing square brackets.
All will work fine in the browser if you omit those square brackets, but the server then doesn't get access
to the selected-list elements, only to the last one. So if you select three elements, omit the square
brackets, then only the third one will be processed by PHP. Of course, we do not want this, so we need to
make sure that the value of the name attribute ends in those square brackets.
Apart from that, everything is pretty easy, similar to before, so let's right get to it and go to the code.
Let's start with the easier list, the color list, because in that case, well, only one element can be
selected, and if there's one it will be in $_POST of 'color'. It's a bit more difficult for the
multi-selection list, so just to recall, it's called languages and has square brackets afterwards, that's a
necessity. In order to access the array of selected elements, we once again use $_POST of, and then the
name, languages. We do not need the square brackets here. Actually, we cannot use them, because then it
would not work. We don't need them here in the key for the $_POST array, we just need it in the HTML markup.
So this is an array, however, if we output an array, PHP is very clever and just outputs array, the word
array, not the contents of the array. Somehow we have to combine those array elements into a string in order to
properly output it. There are several ways of doing that, and one way in PHP, which comes in handy here, is
a function called implode, and implode takes an array and outputs, or returns in that case, all elements
of the array plus a glue string, glue string between each element.
A good glue string, for instance, is a space character. So I would like to have all the values from $_POST
of 'languages', joined with the space character. It looks good, so let's have a look in the browser if it
really looks as good as I think it does. Here we go, again, user name, topsecret password, Gender, arbitrary
favorite color, let's use green, some languages spoken, Comments, and finally, we accept the terms and
conditions, we submit the form. We get the color code, so we get the value, not the caption, and we get
a list of languages which I have selected previously in the multi-selection list.
So far we have processed all the data in the form, and now we have to fine-tune it a little bit more and
then we have made a very important step.