The form works pretty nicely, however, we have made something really, really bad, because we have kind of
trusted user input. We have taken the data being entered into the form and we have just output the data and
sent it back to the browser. However, user input is not trustworthy.
I mean so far we were the only users, and we should trust ourselves, but all other visitors of our website
or users or our web application probably should not be considered trustworthy.
The problem is that the input, in our case, might contain HTML, so if we output the input, then we add HTML
to our page and there are some aspects of HTML, or features of HTML, that we might not want people entering
on our page, for instance, JavaScript. There are a lot of attacks that can be done with JavaScript.
The specific attack is called cross-site scripting, and we need to avoid this, which we do not do yet.
The htmlspecialchars function is built into PHP and it takes care of exactly the attack I mentioned of
HTML special characters in the input. So whenever we output data and send it back to the browser, and the
data we output comes from the user, thus is not trustworthy, we first need to run, for instance,
htmlspecialchars over the data being sent to the browser because it takes care of HTML special characters.
By default, htmlspecialchars takes care of four characters, angle brackets, opening and closing, double
quotes, and the ampersand character. These are four of the five special characters HTML offers, so if you
escape them properly we're all good as long as we output HTMl. There is a fifth one, the single quote.
By default, this is not escaped, also has _____reasons, however, if you use htmlspecialchars, and the first argument is
the string we'd like to escape, if you use the constant and _QUOTES as the second one, we would also
escape the single quotes, just to make it a little bit better.
Now, let's implement this in our HTML form code.
Actually it's pretty easy, at least in this state of our application we just run htmlspecialchars whenever
we refer to the data and output it. We could use end quotes as an argument in order to also escape single
quotes. We do not need this in our example because we are not using any single quotes in our HTML markup,
so this works well enough, and all I need to do is _____ output or well, copy, paste it actually, around
all the other values here, so we have the color. We can also put htmlspecialchars around the return value
of implode. We use it here, we use it here. We could also get rid of the extra unneeded comma in the
output string. Well, and basically that's it, now we've added some security to our form.
Let's try this in the browser. We have a user name, we have a topsecret password, a gender, color, some
languages, and then I tried to inject some HTML in the Comments, so This is a &lt;i&gt;testK&lt;/i&gt;.
I do not try to inject JavaScript here, just some random HTML. Still bad, but in the output we do get the
actual markup but the text doesn't show up as italic, so we've avoided the attack, and so we are pretty good
at this state. We have now processed all of the form data, so as long as we fill out the form completely,
we are good. If not, we'll have some extra work to do.