In a perfect world, all forms are filled out completely, there are no errors, no omitted fields, no attacks,
everything is fine, but of course, that's just not the reality, so we do need to validate all data coming
from the client to the server, because we have to safeguard our application and our server.
Thus, we need to validate all form data. For most form fields that's actually pretty easy,
we just check if we have non-empty values. So if we have a text field, we have a look whether there is
something in the text field or not. We could add some special rules, for instance, three space characters
are not considered as valid input, so we could use something like trim removing white space at the
beginning and at the end of a string, but basically we can also check is there something within the
text field or not. Also, for radio buttons we know that the value of the selected radio button is sent to
the server, so if nothing is sent to the server the radio button obviously hasn't been selected, none of them.
Also, for checkboxes, if no value arrives at the server, the user didn't activate the checkbox.
If the checkbox was mandatory, such as in our example the terms and conditions checkbox, then of course
we have a validation error. For lists we need special treatment.
For instance, if we have our dropdown list, well, currently we always have to pick one of those colors
in the dropdown list, but we could add an extra first entry in the list, a blank entry or an entry that says
please select something, and then we need to find out, well, did we pick that entry, bemuse that entry is
not valid, it is not valid input, please select something is not a valid input.
Also in the multiple-selection list well, we might have a look at which values have been selected and which
ones have not been selected. It really depends on the use case, but basically that's what we need to do.
Of course, in order to provide a great user experience we should consider using JavaScript to do the form
validation. When JavaScript was created in the 1990s, the major use case for JavaScript actually was form
validation. Also HTML5 comes with new form validation features.
This is pretty nice, and gives immediate feedback to the user if there's an error when entering data into
the form fields. However, this is just a usability feature, it does not add any security to the application
because an attacker could just deactivate JavaScript or just send the HTTP request anyway, even if the form
hasn't been completely and validly filled out, so we always have to validate form data on the server, and
that's what we are going to do right now in the code. Our printf statement here shall only be executed if the
form has been submitted, that's what we check here, and if everything is okay, and that's what we like to
find out. By default, we just assume that everything is okay, and then we try to prove the contrary.
In the end we just say, if at the end after validation still everything is okay, then in that case, and only
that case, we output the form data, okay. So, okay is true, and then we'll have a look at the individual
fields. We start with the text field. Now when is the text field not being filled out properly?
First of all, we have to see if there is an entry $_POST of name at all, and we can do this using isset.
So if it's not isset($_POST), then well, we have an error, so we could set ok to false.
However, browsers behave in a specific kind of way with text fields.
If we leave the text field blank, $_POST of name is set to, well, nothing, so we have to add a second check
for that case or if $_POST equals to, and we use three equality signs, which doesn't only compare those
values, but also checks whether both operants have the same data type, the empty string.
So if the field hasn't been set, or is empty, ok is false. Now, of course, we could turn $ok into a, let's
say, string variable, and not only say whether there have been any errors, but also where those errors are,
which fields haven't been filled out completely. We won't do this here because we'd like to make other
concepts clear, but still, it would be rather trivial to do. Now let's continue with those other fields,
and I can do quite an amount of copy and paste here. I just have to fix the indentation once again, and we
go to the password field. The password field counts as a text field, so the code is exactly the same.
The same thing, of course, also holds true for the multi-line text field, so for Comments,
but it's pretty easy actually. We also have the radio buttons, which is more or less the same code,
however, if the radio button value is sent to the server, something must have been picked.
Still there could be an attacker that crafts an HTTP request which sends gender, but no value with gender.
So just recommend we use exactly the same code here in order to find out whether the gender has been sent,
and of course also, because it's related to the radio button, the terms and conditions checkbox has been sent.
So far so good, but there's still two more elements, the two lists.
We first have the color list, and as I mentioned we add another option, and we say this option just has an
empty value. And we add something like, Please select, something like this, right.
So we have a first entry which does not count as valid input, and we have to check for that.
Now if this value is selected, we have value= empty string, so empty string is sent to the server, so our
validation is still true. We can use copy and paste again also for the color selection list, so I just use
color here and color here, and we are good. The last one, and probably the most complex one, although it's
not that bad, is the multi-selection list, the languages list. What could happen?
Well, we could get nothing, so $_POST of languages is not set. In that case we have an error.
The second option is that, well, it is sent, but nothing is in that list.
So how do we find that out? Technically it's an array, right. So we could check two things.
First of all, is it an array? If it's not an array, something went wrong, error, so the form hasn't been
filled out completely. And if it is an array, it has to have at least one value in it, one element.
And we'll check for all of those cases. So let's go up once more, one final, hopefully, copy and paste,
and this time we'll have a look at $_POST of languages. If it's not set, then something is wrong, so
$ok is set to false. Otherwise, if it's set, it could be the case that $_POST of languages just is not an array.
There's a built-in PHP function to check whether something is an array called is_array.
Yes there is an underscore in the function name. There is no underscore in isset.
Well, that's just the way it is,  I won't comment further on that.
So if $_POST of languages is not an array, then something is wrong, and well, third case, if it's an array
it could still be the case thanks to a specifically crafted attack HTTP request, that there are no elements
in the array. The count function gives us the number of elements in an array, so if
count($_POST) is 0, in that case if we have no elements in the array, then well, something is
wrong, so we set $ok to false. So far, so good, let's go to the web browser.
Here we go again. We fill out the form and happen to forget a field.
Let's say I forget to provide my gender. I provide all of the other values, This is a test, I accept the
terms and conditions, but again, I forgot the Gender field, and prior to the form we have the output, right,
so I submit the form and no output because I forgot a field. Now let's do this right.
This time I do provide my gender. I also provide the other fields, submit the form again, and now I get
the output again. So I have a form that validates, more or less, but there is still room for a number of
improvements.