So far our validation has been pretty simplistic. We just check if there is anything being sent from the
browser to us. Of course, we can have a much closer look at the data that's sent to PHP.
We could look if input has the right format or if there was a field, let's say, date of birth, if it's really
a date, and there are various ways of checking the input. The most complex and of course most famous and
most powerful one is using regular expressions. So you can provide an expression that just gives us a
kind of format how the input should look like, so in that case we have a regular expression that checks for
at the beginning of the string, a couple of characters and % character, and then again a couple of characters,
and maybe a dot and so on and so forth, that's an email address essentially, and we can check whether that
email address pattern fits to the input we receive. The function we can use there is called preg_match.
preg stands for Perl Compatible Regular Expressions because PHP supports the Perl syntax, which is kind of
an industry standard, and all the preg_ something functions take care of regular expressions.
It's built in to PHP. preg_match expects a regular expression, and the input and then, well, returns the
matches, so how often does the input contain the search pattern. The catch is, preg_match stops after the
first match, so the return value of preg_match is either 0 or 1. Now since 0 converted to a Boolean is
false, and 1 converted to a Boolean is true, we could just do, if not, preg_match, and well, if there is no
match, then we have an error if we have a match, of course, and there is no error, and so we can amend our
validation rules and as I already mentioned, we could also provide a detailed error message telling user
what's wrong, but well, so far we know the basics of validating form data, and the only thing remaining is
that we need to amend the usability of our form, because as you can see in the browser, all the input is gone,
even if you had a mistake. So if you go back in the browser and, well, we just make an error, so the password
field is never stored by the browser. We submit again, well, we do not get an error message, but we know
that there is an error. However, all the valid input is gone too, and we need to fix that, but this requires
some more coding effort on our part.