In the next and final step, we would like to make sure that the form keeps its values after the form has been
submitted, so even if we forget a field or have any other error, the valid input still is there.
In order to do that, I first have to refactor the code a tiny little bit.
I'd like to introduce some variables which contain either the current or the default values for each and
every field, and I'll call those variables exactly like the form fields.
So I enter the variable $name, I introduce it, and the default value for the name is, well, empty string.
right, because as long as the user does not provide a name, there is no name.
Same goes for the password, and in our example we will prefill the password field.
That's not always a good idea, but just in order to show you how it's done from a technical point of view,
that's the path we are choosing this time. The Comments, multi-line field also, is an empty string,
Well, the Gender, if there is no Gender selected we have nothing, so empty string sounds like a good idea,
same for the terms and conditions. The default color is, well, no color, so empty string.
And the only difference here is languages, list of languages we've chosen, because we should not use an empty
string here. Rremember $_POST, $_GET of languages is an array with all the selected languages, so we just
create an array with no values inside the array, so that's an empty array.
So we introduce the variables here, and then we have our validation, and all we do in our validation is, if we
determine an error, well, we determine the error, otherwise, if everything is okay we store the user input in
the variable, so $name = $_POST of 'name'. So whatever happens, $name contains either the default or the
current value for the name field, and we'll do that same thing for all the other form fields, so $password =
$_POST of 'password', and we do the same thing for the Comments field, so $comments = $_POST of 'comments'.
And it looks a little bit like repetitive work, but in the end it's all worth it, $gender = $_POST of
'gender'. Terms and conditions is next, so $tc = $_POST of tc, same for color else, $color = $_POST of
'color'. And finally, we have the languages field, so if this has been correctly set, it is an array as we
wanted, so $_POST of 'languages' is the array we would like to have.
That's the first step, so now we have those variables always with the correct value, and now we can think
about actually filling those form fields with those values. We start with text fields.
For single line text fields, which also include password fields, we just have to set the value attribute
of the those text or password fields to the value that should appear in those fields, that's what the value
attribute is good for. It's a little bit different for the multi-line text field that we do not have the
input element, we have text area, and the actual content is within the text area element.
That's because we then can also have multi-line input and line breaks, which would be harder to do with
attributes. Now let's implement this directly in the code.
Let's move to those text fields, there we are. Here is the user name text field, and usually what we
would need to do is say, value =, and then "abc", but of course we do not use "abc" here, we use what
the user previously entered into that field, so we have to output the content from PHP, we have to mix
PHP an HTML here, so I just start a php block, close it right away.
So whatever that PHP block outputs goes into the value attribute, and now I'll output the value I want,
and what's the value I want, well, it's in the $name variable. So I just output $name, and then once again
have to remember that there might be HTML special characters inside, so I do an htmlspecialchars($name).
Since I enclosed the attributed value with double quotes, I do not need to escape single quotes here, so I
do not need the end quotes, constant, which I previously mentioned, so well, that's just good enough here.
Same thing holds for the password field, as I mentioned, usually you would not prefill a password field, but
for the sake of demonstration we'll do this right away. So php block here, and then within the php block we
echo the variable we created previously, htmlspecialchars($password).
And practically the same thing here in the comment section, in that case we just do the php block within the
text area field, and there we just say echo htmlspecialchars($comments).
And there we go, now we've prefilled the form fields. These were the easiest ones, the other types of form
fields are a bit more tricky so you have to know HTML a bit more, but once you've done it for a specific
instance of a type of field, you could do it for the others as well.